<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Principles of truth being a declaration of our faith, who are called Quakers, whereby all that wants peace with God  may return into their first state, through the operation of the light and power of God in the great work of regeneration / written by E.B., J.C., W.D., H.S.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6019A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42820</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875801</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875801</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2286:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Principles of truth being a declaration of our faith, who are called Quakers, whereby all that wants peace with God  may return into their first state, through the operation of the light and power of God in the great work of regeneration / written by E.B., J.C., W.D., H.S.</title>
                  <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
                  <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
                  <author>Dewsbury, William, 1621-1688.</author>
                  <author>Parker, Alexander, 1628-1689.</author>
                  <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>151 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Year, 1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Parts of work variously signed, Edward Burrough, John Crook, William Dewsbury, A. (i.e. Alexander) Parker, Humphrey Smith.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 97, 135 numbered 79, 155 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Inner Light.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRINCIPLES OF TRUTH: BEING A Declaration of our FAITH, who are called QUAKERS. WHEREBY All that wants Peace with God may return into their <hi>firſt ſtate,</hi> through the Operation of the LIGHT and Power of God in the great Work of REGENERATION.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>E. B. J. C. W. D. H. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1668.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152237:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152237:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Truths Principles: OR,</hi> Thoſe things about <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which are moſt ſurely believed and received among the People of God, called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>MAny are the Reports that are abroad concerning this People, not only as to their Practices and Deportments, but alſo as to other Doctrines and Beliefs.</p>
               <p>The former, time having in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure reſolved and worn out, as being <hi>the Refuge of Lyes</hi> for the ignorant and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to flee unto; but that ſtormy and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try appearance is well nigh <hi>over and gone,</hi> becauſe the Sun is ſo far riſen, <hi>and the true Light ſo ſhineth,</hi> that moſt begin to ſee that thoſe Reports were but Lyes and Scandals, raiſed as <hi>Fig-leaves</hi> to cover the <hi>nakedneſs</hi> of other Profeſſions, that begun ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152237:3"/>
to appear, through the Light that ſhined in theſe Peoples <hi>Lives and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations.</hi> But though the firſt be gone, yet the the latter ſticks with many as not knowing what they hold as to Doctrine, ſome ſaying, they <hi>deny the Scripture,</hi> and the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body,</hi> and <hi>all Ordinances,</hi> with the <hi>man Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>his Death and Sufferings,</hi> and <hi>imputation of his Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>faith in his Blood,</hi> &amp;c. Wherefore, for the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all that would willingly be reſolved, and know the Truth <hi>as it is in Jeſus,</hi> I have written this ſhort account of their <hi>Faith and Belief;</hi> and if it were poſſible to ſtop the mouthes of the clamorous tongues, before Sentence be given againſt them by ſome ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtroke of the Lord from Heaven, which he will <hi>undoubtedly</hi> in his appointed time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal and make manifeſt, to the <hi>trembling of all hearts</hi> concerned therein, and <hi>tingling of all ears</hi> that ſhall hear thereof, when it ſhall be ſaid to them, <hi>The holy ſhall be holy ſtill; and he that is filthy let him be filthy ſtill,</hi> Rev. 22.11.</p>
               <p>We believe, that the God of all Grace, have given a meaſure of Grace, or ſome <hi>manifeſtation of his Spirit</hi> and Light thereof unto all men, according unto theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152237:3"/>
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.20. and experiences of all men, who (at ſome time or other) do feel ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in their <hi>Hearts and Conſciences,</hi> that doth luſt againſt the Fleſh, and the Fleſh againſt it, and that theſe two <hi>are contrary the one to the other,</hi> one luſting after <hi>evil,</hi> which is evil; and the other after <hi>good,</hi> which is good; the one Carnal, the other Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; the one from Earth, the other from Heaven, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16, 17.</p>
               <p>We believe, By this Gift, Grace and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Almighty, man only can come to know the <hi>true God</hi> truly, what he is, and how he works in the Hearts and Conſciences of people, to regenerate them and make them bear his Image, according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. and experiences of all that ever were <hi>regenerated and born again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We believe, That all the Errors and Miſtakes about God, and the things rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his Kingdom, ſprang and aroſe from mens wandring from this Gift of God, into their <hi>own Imaginations;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, though they <hi>thought themſelves wiſe,</hi> yet they became fools and erred, <hi>their fooliſh hearts being darkened,</hi> according to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152237:4"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. not knowing <hi>the Scriptures, nor the Power of God,</hi> as it is written, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29.</p>
               <p>We believe and know, That this Gift and Grace of God appears in and unto all men, that all may be without <hi>excuſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing</hi> for the evil, and <hi>excuſing</hi> for the good, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15, 16. ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto man <hi>what is good,</hi> and reproving of him in his own Conſcience for the evil, whether thoughts, words, or deeds: and that this <hi>reproof of inſtruction</hi> is the way of life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23.</p>
               <p>We believe, That as the <hi>true God</hi> and <hi>Eternal Life</hi> is known only by the light of this <hi>Gift</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> according unto the Scriptures, from which Light and Spirit of God came the Scriptures, both from the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> as it is written, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. ſo can they only be <hi>read,</hi> as truly to be <hi>believed, fulfilled</hi> and <hi>practiſed,</hi> in the Light and power of the ſame; and all that are out of this Spirit muſt needs be <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>unlearned,</hi> in the Apoſtles ſenſe, <hi>who wreſt the Scriptures to their own deſtruction,</hi> as it is written: for <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were <hi>unlearned men</hi> outwardly, not knowing <hi>Letters,</hi> but inwardly <hi>read</hi> in the knowledge of this Light and Spirit of God, and <hi>wreſted not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152237:4"/>
the Scriptures,</hi> Acts 4.13. 2 Pet. 3.16.</p>
               <p>We believe, according to the Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.3. That whereſoever the Power of God is not known within, there <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is hid,</hi> and unknown, <hi>unto them that are loſt, in whom the God of this World hath blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the minds of them that believe not, leſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them,</hi> and God ſhould heal them; becauſe it is only by the Light of Chriſt, <hi>the Power of God,</hi> that the Creature comes truly to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his loſt and undone eſtate; from which ſight ariſeth the true ſenſe in the heart of the Creature, that makes him cry out of his wretchedneſs by reaſon of the <hi>body of Sin and Death,</hi> which neceſſitates him to look out for a Saviour, whom God manifeſteth in and by the ſame Light, <hi>that ſhines in the heart,</hi> on purpoſe, <hi>to give the Light of the knowledge of the Glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, God's Image,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God healeth the Soul: And therefore doth the Devil, <hi>the god of the world,</hi> ſtrive ſo much by the gifts of the pleaſures, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, vanities, and luſts that are in the World, which he preſenteth to men and women now, as he did to Chriſt, in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152237:5"/>
dayes of his fleſh, when he ſhewed to him <hi>all the world, with its glory;</hi> which <hi>glory</hi> is <hi>the Luſt of the fleſh, the Luſt of the eye, and the Pride of life,</hi> whatever may make this Life happy (as it were) in the things that may pride it, or lift it up <hi>to ſit as a Queen:</hi> And as men and women take and receive theſe gifts from the <hi>god of this world,</hi> their minds are blinded becauſe they believe not in the Light which ſheweth them the vanities of all the gifts of <hi>the god of this world;</hi> which gifts the Devil knows (if they be received) will ſo <hi>blind the minds</hi> of them that receive them, that they will not come to be ſenſible in the true Light, of their loſt conditions, ſo as to cry unto God from the deep and true ſenſe; for then God, out of the depths of his Love and Mercy, could not but <hi>heal them:</hi> And therefore, leſt the true Light ſhould ſhine <hi>into them,</hi> to give them the ſenſible know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of themſelves, and God ſhould heal them, the Devil (as <hi>god of the World,</hi> by the things of the world) endeavours to <hi>blind the mind</hi> (not the brain-knowledge, but the hearty-feeling ſence within in the mind) leſt <hi>the Light within</hi> ſhould ſo ſhine as God ſhould <hi>heal them;</hi> and all the buſlings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152237:5"/>
of Satan with his gifts, are but to blind the mind within, leſt God ſhould heal the ſoul, that complains to him from the true ſight and ſence of his Miſery, as in himſelf.</p>
               <p>By this <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Gift within,</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That <hi>to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s (though in the world there be Lords many, and Gods many) there is but ONE GOD, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> witneſſed <hi>within man</hi> only by the Spirit of Truth, that manifeſts both the Father and the Son, and yet <hi>theſe three are one, and agree in one;</hi> and he that honours the Father, honours the Son that proceeds from him; and he that denies the Spirit, denies both the Father and the Son, and is <hi>Anti-Chriſt;</hi> but he that believes in the Spirit, and is led by it, is the Son of God; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>As many as are the Sons of God, are led by the Spirit of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We believe, The Scriptures bare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto, and teſtifie of Chriſt; but they ſay, <hi>The Witneſs of God is greater than them; The Spirit it ſelf bearing witneſs with our ſpirits, that we are the Sons of God:</hi> for it is not the Scriptures without the Spirit, nor the Spirit contrary to the Scriptures, but the Spirits diſcovering the Will of God in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152237:6"/>
heart, or opening of the Scriptures in its own time and way, and not in or by the will of man, but as it ſelf pleaſeth (who ſearcheth all, even the deep things of God, and manifeſts them unto the Soul) which giveth the perfect ſound and ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: for, ſaid Chriſt, <hi>The Spirit ſhall take of mine, and ſhew them unto you.</hi> And as holy men gave forth the Scriptures 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. ſo holy men, and they only come truly to underſtand them, and not proud and ungodly men; becauſe their hearts and lives do not anſwer the hearts and lives of thoſe that gave them forth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> face anſwereth face in a Glaſs. And this we believe to be the reaſon, why ſo long preaching (by men of corrupt minds, who have, and do handle the words deceitfully for ſelfiſh ends, and filthy lucre ſake) hath brought forth ſo little fruit, and been to ſo little purpoſe, except to their Purſes and Bellies; for <hi>had they believed, and therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpoken, and ſtood in Gods Counſel, they ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have profited their Hearers,</hi> Jer. 23.21, 22 23, to the end.</p>
               <p>Through this Gift we believe, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt Ieſus (the Son of God) was mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſt in the fleſh in the fulneſs of time. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152237:6"/>
this we know by the ſame Spirit, by which our Fathers believed he ſhould come, and <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw his day, by the ſame we do believe he is come, and do ſee his day; as alſo by the Prophets and Apoſtles Writing; which <hi>twofold Cord is not eaſily broken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We believe alſo according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth, That this <hi>ſame Jeſus hath God highly exalted, and given him a Name above every name, that whoſoever believes in him ſhall not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life;</hi> and that there is not another name where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man can be ſaved, than this Name of Jeſus Chriſt; nor is Remiſſion of Sins to be preached by any other name But as we do not believe that the outward Letters and Syllables are that Name that is to be bowed to by the outward knee, no more than the Letters or Syllables in the words, <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto God,</hi> who is a Spirit, <hi>every knee ſhall bow,</hi> Iſa. 45.23. but the Name which ſaves is the Power and Arm of God, that brings Salvation from Sin, and makes every Soul that names it, to depart from Iniquity, This is that Name which was preached, and which is preached through Faith, in which Name Remiſſion of Sin is obtained: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152237:7"/>
was the outward word, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> given him, as his outward name; <hi>Thou ſhalt call his Name JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, for he ſhall ſave his People from their Sins:</hi> [Mark] <hi>for he ſhall ſave,</hi> &amp;c. So that which ſaves, is the Name which is to be believed in, which is that Arm of God that brings Salvation, <hi>when no eye pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, neither is there any to help;</hi> the Power of God that then ſaves is that Grace that comes from the fulneſs of Chriſt the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: And without this virtue, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus</hi> are but empty names, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. <hi>No man can ſay, that Jeſus is the LORD, but by the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We believe alſo, That this <hi>Jeſus</hi> died for or becauſe of Sin, and roſe again for the Juſtification of thoſe that believe in him, as well as to manifeſt to all the world, that he was the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and that he thereby <hi>ſpoiled Principalities and Powers,</hi> and <hi>triumphed over them openly,</hi> and <hi>led Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity captive</hi> in his own perſon; yet we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and know by his Grace in our hearts, that as his Name, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> without Vertue and Power is but an empty word; ſo his Dying, without man's Conformity to his Death, or being planted into the likeneſs thereof, or being crucified with Chriſt (as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152237:7"/>
ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.) will not profit man, as to the Salvation of his Soul, no more than the naming of his outward name <hi>[Jeſus]</hi> doth at this day make people to depart from Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. For we believe, and are ſure, that man muſt dye inwardly, as well as Chriſt died outwardly, and muſt be put to death in his fleſh, as Chriſt was in his; for <hi>he that is in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God,</hi> Rom. 8.8. <hi>neither ceaſe from ſin;</hi> but <hi>he that is dead, is freed from ſin,</hi> Rom. 6.7. And yet mans dying unto Sin, and the Root and Principle of it in himſelf, is ſo far from making void Chriſt's Death in his own perſon, that it eſtabllſheth it to all thoſe ends and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for which it was intended of the Father. As the Cures which the Phyſitian doth, manifeſt and eſtabliſh his skill and ability, ſo doth mans dying unto Sin and Self, and living unto God, manifeſt and eſtabliſh the Vertue and Power of Chriſt's Death: for as man manifeſts his being riſen with Chriſt, by his ſeeking the things that are above, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 2. ſo doth he manifeſt his knowledge of the Death of Chriſt, by his <hi>being crucified with Chriſt, and bearing about in his body the dyings of the Lord Jeſus:</hi> for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152237:8"/>
as it is not an outward belief, gathered from the Letter, that will change the heart and life (though the Judgment and Opinion it may) ſo it is not a belief from the Hiſtory, or Letter only, that can give man a ſaving-knowledge of the Death of Chriſt, but he muſt have the ſame <hi>Glory and Power of the Father</hi> in meaſure, working in him there, to beget Faith in his heart, that he may believe unto Salvation from his own fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and righteouſneſs, as well as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs with his mouth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. and muſt have that <hi>Spirit</hi> in him <hi>quickning his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal body,</hi> as well as to believe that it was <hi>in Chriſt, and raiſed up him from the dead,</hi> Rom. 8.11. And this man, whoever he be, bond or free, that thus believes the Death of Chriſt, and its ſatisfaction to God, as well as its uſefulneſs to man, cannot make it void, nor divide it and its vertue upon the Soul that thus knows it, but will ſay, Here is a dying man, witneſſing the Death of Chriſt, and nevertheleſs the ſame man living with Chriſt, and concluding, if Chriſt had not died, man muſt have periſhed in his ſin: this being the way found out by God to recover him; whereby he knows Chriſt, <hi>and Him Crucified,</hi> and what the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152237:8"/>
preaching of the Croſs of Chriſt is, which is <hi>fooliſhneſs to them that periſh,</hi> but to them that are <hi>ſaved, the Wiſdom of God, and the Power of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.</p>
               <p>By this Gift of God in our hearts, we further believe, That Chriſt Jeſus <hi>roſe again from the dead,</hi> according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>and ſits at Gods right hand</hi> in a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body: And we believe that our low eſtates and humble bodies ſhall be <hi>made like unto his glorious Body, through the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his mighty Power, whereby he is able to ſubdue all things unto himſelf; and that this mortality ſhall put on Immortallity.</hi> For though we believe that Chriſt Jeſus hath lighted every man with his Light, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man may come to know himſelf loſt and undone, as before is ſaid; yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not every man ſaved, though the <hi>Grace</hi> that appears to all men is <hi>ſufficient in it ſelf;</hi> but ſome have the Grace of God beſtowed upon them in vain, <hi>not liking to retain God in their knowledge,</hi> though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within them ſhews them what is good: <hi>But they reject the Counſel of God within, or againſt themſelves to their own deſtruction,</hi> Luke 7.30. (ſee the Margent) and yet it doth not follow that the Grace
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152237:9"/>
is inſufficient of it ſelf, no more than it follows that Chriſt's Death is inſufficient, becauſe he <hi>taſted death for every man,</hi> and yet every man is not ſaved. Neither doth <hi>Regeneration,</hi> or the believing in the <hi>Light</hi> of Chriſt <hi>within,</hi> make <hi>void</hi> the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Sufferings</hi> of Chriſt <hi>without</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> no more than believing the Scripture-teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony without, concerning Chriſt's Death, makes void the work of Regeneration and Mortification within; but as the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, ſo I ſay in this, <hi>For as the man is not without the woman, neither is the woman without the man in the Lord:</hi> even ſo is not the Death and Sufferings of Chriſt without at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be made void and of none effect by any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, neither doth the <hi>Light within</hi> make that of none effect without, but both in the Lord anſwers his Will: For though there is, and may be, a knowledge and belief of what Chriſt did and ſuffered without the Gates, in his own Body, upon the Tree, and yet Sin alive in the heart, and the work of Regeneration not known; yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo where the <hi>Light within</hi> is belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on, and obeyed, ſo as to have its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect work in the heart, to regenerate and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152237:9"/>
make all things new, and to be of God; this man can never make void what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered without: And yet this New-birth, or Chriſt formed within, and dwelling in the heart by Faith, doth not limit or confine Chriſt to be only within, and not without alſo, but both within and without, according to the good pleaſure of the Father to reveal and make him known; for, <hi>he fills all things, and the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain him,</hi> and yet is he at Gods right hand far above all Heavens, in a glorious body.</p>
               <p>And we alſo believe the <hi>Reſurrection of the Juſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> to <hi>Condemnation,</hi> according unto the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>great Day;</hi> and then ſhall every ſeed have <hi>its own body,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.36, 37. which we ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe: <hi>For if the dead riſe not, we are of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> But becauſe we dare not be ſo <hi>fooliſhly inquiſitive,</hi> as to ſay, <hi>With what bodies ſhall they ariſe;</hi> therefore do ſome ſay, we deny both the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body of Chriſt, and of all that are or ſhall be dead: But this alſo is falſe; for <hi>every man ſhall be raiſed in his own order:</hi> but <hi>Chriſt the firſt fruits,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.23.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152237:10"/>
And we believe they ſhall be raiſed with the ſame bodies, ſo far as a natural and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual, corruptible and incorruptible, terre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrial and celeſtial can be the ſame.</p>
               <p>We further believe, according unto the Scriptures, concerning Faith, That thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Faith</hi> is only true, which is God's Gift and hath Chriſt Jeſus, the Power of God for its author and object, and is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guiſhed from the dead faith by its fruits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For though in deſcription and definition they may carry a reſemblance, yet in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are as different as a living man is from a dead, which wants not form or ſhape, but life and power. So ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>James, As the body without a ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is dead, ſo is Faith without Works;</hi> even ſo is that Faith which ſtands in the wiſdom of words, and not in the Power of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> By the one, man is kept in captivity to the world and the things of it, but by the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he hath <hi>victory over the World,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.4 and the <hi>Seal</hi> and <hi>Witneſs</hi> thereof in his own <hi>heart,</hi> whereby it is <hi>purified,</hi> and God is ſeen; for the <hi>pure in heart ſee God,</hi> Matth 5.8. This Faith differs men now, and their worſhips, as it did <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel:</hi> For, <hi>By Faith</hi> Abel <hi>offered up a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152237:10"/>
Sacrifice then</hi> Cain, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. By this living Faith, <hi>Abel</hi> ſaw beyond the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice unto Chriſt, the firſt-born of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>firſtling of the Flock,</hi> which he offered; and therefore God had reſpect unto <hi>Abel</hi> and his offering, but God rejected <hi>Cain</hi> and his offering; though he had Faith to belive it to be his duty, yet ſticking in the Form, and not flying on the wing of Faith unto Chriſt, the <hi>One Offering,</hi> he miſſed the Mark, as all have done ever ſince, that have gone in <hi>Cains</hi> way of worſhipping, as well as killing men about Worſhip. But we believe that Faith to be only true and ſaving, that flies over ſelf-righteouſneſs, as well as filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, unto the Fountain of Life in Chriſt; which Faith hath nothing of man in it, but is <hi>as the breath of Life by which the ſoul lives;</hi> not a bare aſſent of the truth of a propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the natural underſtanding, but the ſouls cleaving unto God, out of a naturalneſs between Chriſt and the Soul; and ſo live ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by relation, than bare credit, or deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate adventure and hazard: Not looking at its doing to commend it, but God's Love and Bounty in Chriſt, the Light, to receive it: and yet holineſs is its delight, and he can no more live out of it, than the Fiſh upon the dry Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152237:11"/>We believe, That this <hi>Faith keeps</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mind <hi>pure,</hi> and the heart <hi>clean,</hi> throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>ſprinkling</hi> of the <hi>heart</hi> from an evil <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> by the <hi>Blood of Jeſus,</hi> which remi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Sin, and juſtifies the Soul, through th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> virtue of this Blood received into the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by this living Faith, which receives all it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power and virtue from Chriſt, in whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> abides as its root and object, whereby <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> is witneſſed <hi>from Sin, not in Sin</hi> Rom. 6.22. <hi>But now being made free from Sin, and become ſervants unto God, you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your fruits unto Holineſs, and the end ever<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We believe, That <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctification are diſtinguiſhed,</hi> but <hi>not divided</hi> for as he that ſanctifieth and juſtifieth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one, ſo do theſe go together, and whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Soul hath the greateſt ſence of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation upon it, through the vertue of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Blood of Jeſus, by the Living Faith, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is it moſt in love with Holineſs, and at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greateſt diſtance from Sin and Evil: and whenever there is a failing in Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is alſo ſome eclipſe of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in the eye of the Soul, until Faith hath recovered its ſtrength again, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loſt by ſins prevailing. For, as the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152237:11"/>
and cleareſt ſight is in the brighteſt day, ſo is it with the Soul, when it is moſt in the brightneſs and beauty of Holineſs, its Juſtification appears moſt glorious, and its Union and Communion moſt ſweet and laſting; and ſo like two Twins, as they are much of an age, ſo they are like one to the other: And <hi>what God hath joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let no man put aſunder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We alſo by this Light believe, That Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with the Father is only in Chriſt, and by <hi>his</hi> Righteouſneſs <hi>made ours,</hi> or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto <hi>us;</hi> not by the creaturely skill, but by the applicatory act of Gods gift of Grace, whereby the Soul feels the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between ſelf-applying by its own Faith, and God applying by its Spirit, and ſo making Chriſt unto the Soul, <hi>Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption:</hi> So that we believe, and are ſure, that there is a great difference between Imputation, as it is the act of mans ſpirit, and as it is the act of Free Grace, without mans forcing. And ſo we diſtinguiſh between Imagination and Imputation, between reckoning or imputing that is real, and reckoning or imputation that is not real, but a fiction and imagination in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152237:12"/>
will and power. And becauſe we are againſt the latter, we are clamoured upon, as if we denied the Imputation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, when it is only unto thoſe that are not made righteous by it <hi>to walk as he alſo walked.</hi> For, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, It is not he that ſaith he is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous by the imputation of Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, but <hi>he that doth Righteouſneſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> righteous, even as Chriſt is Righteous,</hi> 1 Joh 3.7. he that believes otherwiſe is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And yet it is not Acts of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, as done by us, nor as inherent in us, as acts, by which we are accepted of God, and juſtified before him, but by Chriſt the Author and Worker of thoſe acts in us and for us, whereby we know that we are in him, and he in us, and we hold him as our Head, into whom al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things are gathered together into one, even in him.</p>
               <p>We further believe, That God is only to be worſhipped, and not any likeneſs that man makes unto himſelf of God, from any view, ſight and knowledge that he hath had of him: but in every act and ſervice, man is to know what ſubſtantially, as well as whom ſpeculatively or notionally he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152237:12"/>
worſhippeth: as is is written, <hi>John</hi> 4.22. <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what: we know what we worſhip; for Salvation is of the Jews.</hi> And he that thus worſhips the Father, honours the Son by the ſame Spirit, which is one with the Father and the Son; in which Spirit only God is worſhipped, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the form of its own chuſing and manifeſting of himſelf in and by, according unto the good pleaſure of the Father, who is a Spirit, and limits man unto the Spirit's Form, but allows not man to limit the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit unto his form, though it be not of his inventing originally, but of the Father: yet man muſt no more limit God unto it, then he could command God to appear in it at firſt. For as he choſe it himſelf, ſo he hath reſerved liberty to leave it at his pleaſure, <hi>who works all things after the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his own Will, which he hath purpoſed in himſelf,</hi> that the Gift of the knowledge of the <hi>Myſtery of his Will,</hi> might for ever be acknowledged to be of his Grace, and for the riches of the glory thereof, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. and man be bound, but God free: Man bound to wait in the Light for Gods Movings, but God free to move in whom, to what, and when he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152237:13"/>
pleaſeth: then man is to go, when he ſaith <hi>Go;</hi> and come, when he ſaith, <hi>Come;</hi> and ſuch Servants <hi>do ſerve him:</hi> And then there is no more Curſe, as in the dayes of <hi>Will-worſhip, and voluntary Humility, but the Throne of God, and of the Lamb,</hi> Col. 2.18 23. Rev. 22.3, 4. <hi>And they ſhall ſee his Face, and his Name ſhall be on their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We believe alſo, That this Worſhip is ſpiritual (and not carnal) in all its Parts and Ordinances, and not to be impoſed by any outward force, but performed by the inward leading of Gods holy Spirit, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the holy men of God were led and guided in the days paſt, who gave forth the Scriptures: all impoſitions of Worſhip outward, being only enjoyned under the <hi>firſt Covenant,</hi> that made nothing perfect, <hi>until the time of Reformation,</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.10. But Chriſt being come, there is an end as well of ſuch Impoſitions, as of the <hi>Meats and Drinks, and divers Baptiſms, and carnal Ordinances,</hi> they being all but temporary, and in order unto an end; but all to vail to Chriſt, the ſum and ſubſtance of all, <hi>[the firſt]</hi> pointed at by all, and <hi>[the laſt]</hi> ending of all, <hi>the Amen.</hi> And he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152237:13"/>
that thus worſhips God in Chriſt, his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are ſpiritual and not carnal; and his Faith carries him beyond his Works, with righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> and preſerves him that he is not drowned in the Form, like <hi>Cain;</hi> neither falls he ſhort of the glory of God, nor of his aſſurance of Acceptance with him.</p>
               <p>We believe, There is one Baptiſm ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm.</hi> And this Baptiſm is Spiritual, of which <hi>John</hi>'s Water was but a figure, <hi>John</hi> 1.31. <hi>That he ſhould be made manifeſt to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>therefore am I come, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing with Water,</hi> ſaith <hi>John:</hi> and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. <hi>The like figure whereunto, even Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm doth alſo now ſave us: not the putting away the filth of the Fleſh, but the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This one Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ual Baptiſm into the Name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that which ſaves, the Water being but a figure, that Chriſt might be manifeſt to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had divers Baptiſms impoſed on them untill the time of Reformation; but Chriſt the Subſtance being come, the Shadows flee away. And yet where-ever any are commanded now by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152237:14"/>
that commanded the Believers to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> baptized in the dayes paſt, either for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> furtherance of the Goſpel, or tryal of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Faith, we judge them not. But this obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience is very rare to be found; and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could heartily deſire, that all would con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider ſeriouſly, whether <hi>literal ſayings</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerved only by outward reading, hearin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the ear, or <hi>inward impulſes</hi> upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart by the Divine Power, are the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tives unto Obedience in this kind. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> honeſty and uprightneſs of heart may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heard, we believe and know, the man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dead ſouls every-where, notwithſtandin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Baptiſms, will be as ſo many witne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes againſt them, by their grovling upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the earth, as ſo many ſlain and <hi>killed</hi> me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the <hi>Letter,</hi> while the Spirits quickning have not been known in the true Baptiſm into death. For we find by daily experi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences, that moſt men and women live lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s <hi>lean Kine,</hi> only to <hi>eat up the fat</hi> and to envy thoſe that are not ſo lean ſoul'd as themſelves.</p>
               <p>We believe alſo, That as there is on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true ſaving Baptiſm, ſo there is one Bread or Body of Chriſt, which all the Saints d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feed upon; and though they be many, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152237:14"/>
to perſons, yet their Bread is but one, and they all in it but one Bread: And this we believe is <hi>the fleſh that came down from Heaven,</hi> John 6.33. Though the outward <hi>Jews</hi> now, as then, murmur at him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaid, <hi>I am the Bread which came down from Heaven,</hi> ver. 41, 42. But Chriſt, (ver. 45.) to ſtop their murmuring, tells them, that the knowledge of this Myſtery was only revealed unto them whom God (and not man) teacheth, and no more than are <hi>taught of God,</hi> can ſet ſeal and ſubſcribe unto this <hi>Truth in Jeſus;</hi> though we believe alſo, that Jeſus took outward bread, and brake it, and gave it to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, as the Scriptures ſaith; and this was a figure of his Body (that was to be pierced and broken upon the Tree) and a ſhew, to ſhew forth his Death until he came.</p>
               <p>And we believe he did ariſe again, and appear unto his Diſciples; <hi>And all that believed were together, and had [All things Common] &amp;c. And they continued daily with one accord in the Temple, breaking bread from houſe to houſe, did eat their meat with gladneſs and ſingleneſs of heart, praiſing God, and having favour with all the people,</hi> Acts 2.44, 45, 46, 47. And we believe that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152237:15"/>
the Apoſtle, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. ſaith true, where he ſaith, <hi>When ye come together therefore in one place, this is not to eat the Lords Supper.</hi> And all that he ſpeaks in that chapter is not to perpetuate that outward breaking of Bread, otherwiſe than as the Believers did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that were <hi>filed with the holy Ghoſt in ſingleneſs of heart,</hi> as before is ſaid: and yet we judge not thoſe who break out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Bread, and drink outward Wine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded ſo to do, and put in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thereby of the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, by <hi>the Remembrancer, the Spirit of Truth,</hi> which is appointed by the Father <hi>to lead into all Truth.</hi> But to do it by imitation, or tradition only, (as moſt do it, if not all at this day) we know it is not an Offering unto God in Righteouſneſs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we believe this to be the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Body and Blood of Chriſt;</hi> and yet <hi>the eating of the Fleſh, and drinking of the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> we believe man muſt know and witneſs, or he hath <hi>no life in him,</hi> Joh. 6.53, 54, 55. And we believe that many are ſtriving now in their ſpirits, as the Jews did, verſe 52, ſaying, <hi>How can this man give us his Fleſh to eat?</hi> And not only the Jews, but many of his Diſciples ſaid,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152237:15"/>
                  <hi>This is a hard ſaying, who can bear it?</hi> ver. 60. and at verſe 63. he tells them, <hi>It is the Spirit that quickeneth, the Fleſh profiteth nothing. The words that I ſpeak unto you they are Spirit, and they are Life.</hi> And he that hears and underſtands theſe words that are <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> will not be offended at what I have ſpoken of the <hi>Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the ſame Spirit and Grace we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That Prayer is an Ordinance of God, when performed by his Spirit, in its words, (and not thoſe which mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom teacheth) or without words, <hi>by ſighs and groanes which cannot be uttered,</hi> and theſe ſo often as the Spirit it ſelf pleaſeth: But the Form without the Spirit, whether it be by words of other mens framing, or words of man's own ſpirit, according to his will, time, and manner; this is not the Prayer that <hi>prevails with God.</hi> And we believe that there is none ſo weak and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, but this Spirit proffers his help at ſome time or other, though man regardeth it not. And the more mans mind is gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within from all viſibles, the more he comes to be ſenſible of the Movings and Stirrings of this Spirit, in its ſecret cryes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152237:16"/>
unto God, anſwerable to the wants of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man or woman, in whom it moves and cryes And by the due watching thereunto, we be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieve and know <hi>the Spirit of Prayer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Adoption, that cries unto God,</hi> comes to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcerned and diſtinguiſhed from a man'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own ſpirit and will.</p>
               <p>We believe by the ſame gift of Grace that there are <hi>ſeveral Miniſtrations, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veral Operations,</hi> according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. and all <hi>by the ſame Spirit,</hi> as before and after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Law by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and after by <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and in all theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Miniſtration had acceptance with God through the management of the Spirit, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> its rejection and diſlike of God for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> want thereof. And by this Spirit were th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scriptures give forth, and the holy me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God did <hi>ſpeak, propheſie, preach and pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as they were moved;</hi> and for want of it, <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> letter did, and doth kill.</hi> And for the fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther appearance and pouring out of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit, anſwerable unto the work and ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vice that God had for them to do, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were to wait, as Chriſt commanded hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſciples to do at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to <hi>receive th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Promiſe of the Father:</hi> For by this Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he that ſpeaks, <hi>ſpeaks as the Oracle of God</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152237:16"/>
And therefore, as it was the practice of the People of God in old time, to wait for the moving and ſtirring of this Spirit, that they might ſpeak, <hi>as it gave them utterance,</hi> in the <hi>evidence and demonſtration</hi> thereof; ſo do this People (called <hi>Quakers</hi>) now; and according to its moving in their hearts they miniſter, according to the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, whereby they underſtand both what, and when to ſpeak, and when to be ſilent; as alſo, who are they that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and ſpeak in their own wills, <hi>above the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> which the Apoſtle was carefull alwayes to be in ſubjection to, leſt he ſhould make it void, by ſpeaking the words which mans wiſdom teacheth; and therefore, as the Saints did, ſo <hi>we do believe, and therefore we ſpeak:</hi> And ſuch Preaching and Speaking in Faith, as well as Praying in Faith, is acceptable unto God, as his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>And we further believe by the ſame Spirit, that the ſum of all Religion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Truth, and the ſignification of the word [Religion] is, <hi>Man not at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in his will, but bound again unto God, by his having given to him, by the Light of Chriſt within, the true ſight and knowledge of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152237:17"/>
himſelf, as in himſelf, as loſt and undone fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ever, and from this ſight a true ſence to ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> upon and remain with him;</hi> from wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpring unutterably groans and cryes unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, under the weight of the burthen an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wretchedneſs, by reaſon of the body o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sin and Death, and then when there wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> none to help or pitty in this ſtate, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mercy ſhewed in Chriſt the Arm of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is revealed as an help, neither ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor known, where, how, or when to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> at it, or meet with it; And this begets i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the heart of that man or woman, in, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto whom it is thus revealed, thanks an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praiſes unto God, for this <hi>Gift</hi> and <hi>Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation</hi> of his Son, in this needfull tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whom the Soul ſees to be the Gift of <hi>Ete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we believe and know, upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> of God, is founde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> built and eſtabliſhed the <hi>Everlaſting Cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant</hi> (whereby not only all men, may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaved for its <hi>ability,</hi> but ſome ſhall be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved becauſe for its <hi>prevalency, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> like to the Covenant he made with our F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers.</hi> And although <hi>all mankind</hi> is not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved, yet it is not becauſe either of <hi>inſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiency</hi> in this Covenant, or becauſe of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152237:17"/>
                  <hi>weakneſs of the Grace</hi> that appears in, and unto all men; but becauſe of <hi>mans will, loving death, and chuſing his own deluſions,</hi> whereby <hi>his deſtruction is of himſelf,</hi> and God <hi>clear</hi> of his <hi>blood</hi> in the free tender of his Grace, Gift, and <hi>ſtriving of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within him.</hi> For we know aſſuredly, according to the Scriptures of Truth, and Experience of all ſouls that ever were truly converted to God, that though <hi>by Grace man is ſaved, not of himſelf,</hi> but <hi>by the Free Fift,</hi> yet as the old World did, and thoſe rebellious <hi>Jews,</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. who, as did their Fathers, ſo did they, <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſiſt the holy Ghoſt;</hi> ſo do men now. And yet in the tender of this Grace, and ſtriving of his Spirit, the Lord is a God ſo hiding himſelf in the management of this Striving and Miniſtration of his Spirit, as if it wholly depended upon mans choice and conſenting, that mans will, as to him, is (as it were) free in rejecting or accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <hi>Life and Death being ſet before him;</hi> whereby in the Wiſdom of God, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity of his Nature, as it came out of the hands of his Maker, hath an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by this dealing of God, to put forth it ſelf; ſo that man is as free in the choice,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152237:18"/>
as he is in the refuſal of the tender of Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy and help, and that with an <hi>equal indiffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rency,</hi> as it appears to him in this ſtate notwithſtanding afterwards, in the furthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> growth in this Grace and Knowledge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, he ſees clearly and convincingly that the Grace (that wrought hiddenl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from his ſight and knowledge, in the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> working, tender, and miniſtration of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> towards him) gained his conſent throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> its own prevalency in the Love of God, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which ſight and ſence <hi>ſelf</hi> comes to be <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred,</hi> and the <hi>free Love</hi> ſo <hi>admired,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he knows from firſt to laſt, all was of <hi>Grace</hi> and that <hi>free;</hi> that <hi>ſelf</hi> is not able to chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lenge any thing as due from what it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> done, but <hi>all of gift;</hi> and yet, as before with ſuch an equal indifferency on man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> account: ſo that God may and will appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be juſt, both in condemning and ſaving and <hi>the Juſtifier freely of all that believe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jeſus the Light of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, let all take heed how they diſlike this Miniſtration of God, and <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his Spirit in their Hearts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> under colour and pretence of its <hi>inſufficiency;</hi> and therefore they will not come to him, becauſe his drawings and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152237:18"/>
are not ſo ſtrong as they would have them to be, looking for ſuch an overpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and irreſiſtibleneſs, as they are not able to withſtand and gainſay; leſt ſuch periſh through a wilfull neglect, and for want of ſtretching out their hand when the Lord holds out his, and ſo they periſh in <hi>the ditch,</hi> with a vain expectation of further power; or cry in their mouthes, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us!</hi> and ſo with the Sluggard; while they cry, <hi>Yet a little more ſlumber and folding of the hands to ſleep, their Garden is overgrown with weeds, and their backs cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with rags, and they beg in harveſt;</hi> whilſt others that have <hi>ſown in tears,</hi> not fainting, <hi>do in due time reap in joy;</hi> and <hi>not deſpiſing the crums that fell from the table,</hi> nor <hi>the day of ſmall things,</hi> witneſs the <hi>preſence of their Beloved, come down into his Garden, and walking among the Lillies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let theſe things be truly conſidered, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and weighed in the true Ballance of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> leſt any Soul periſh through the falſe weight and meaſure; ſo ſhall my ſoul rejoyce that any have eſcaped the Net, of the Fowler through the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the <hi>true Light,</hi> and God have all the Glory, unto whom alone it belongs,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152237:19"/>
and man <hi>aſhamed, confounded, his mout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtopped,</hi> and <hi>he laid in the duſt forever;</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then ſhall my end be <hi>anſwered</hi> in writin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe things.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Crook.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Perſwaſions in Matters of Religion.</head>
               <p>THere is the Natural man, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual man, and there are the Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of each in and about Matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. There is the Perſwaſion of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and the Perſwaſion of <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Perſwaſion of <hi>Reaſon</hi> is that Belief which man receives into his mind or heart from the exerciſe of the Reaſoning Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and this Perſwaſion in Matters of Religion is but mans Opinion or Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which how certain or infallible ſo ever it appears to him, yet may be ſhaken by a demonſtration or evidence of a higher kind of nature.</p>
               <p>The Perſwaſion of <hi>Faith,</hi> is that Belief which the New-Creature receives into the renewing-Mind, from the Evidence
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152237:19"/>
and Demonſtration of the Spirit, which openeth and manifeſteth the things of the Spirit, unto that mind which is begotten and renewed by it. And this Perſwaſion is certain and infallible, however it may be ſtruck at and battered, by the reaſonings of the wiſe earthly part, even in that very man, whoſe heart is thus perſwaded, by the Light of the Spirit of God, concerning the things of Gods Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Now the loweſt Perſwaſion of <hi>Faith</hi> is higher, and of a more noble nature then the higheſt Perſwaſion of <hi>Reaſon:</hi> becauſe <hi>Faith</hi> is of an higher Principle, and of a deeper nature and ground, then Mans Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is: But this (becauſe it appears not in mans ſphear, but rather out of it, and is contrary to the line and reach of his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) is accounted by him <hi>fooliſhneſs and madneſs.</hi> Thus is the Wiſdom of God (and the Children thereof) judged and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by man in his day.</p>
               <p>And how can it be otherwiſe? How can the wiſdom of man but judge that as fooliſhneſs, whoſe beauty and excellency is hid from its eye? But this is, becauſe the wiſdom of man is out of its place, not ſubjected to the Wiſdom of God, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152237:20"/>
above it: therefore (as a curſe unto it) is it ſuffered to lift up it ſelf in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs againſt, and ſo to perſecute the pure Wiſdom of God and the birth thereof, that it might fall, and be broken, and ſnared, and taken, and its day deſervedly come to an end, and be ſhut up in the ſhadows and chambers of eternal darkneſs.</p>
               <p>But what ear of Man can hear this! Surely none that is whole in the line of Man's wiſdom, reaſon and underſtanding, but that alone which is bruiſed, broken, and in ſome meaſure daſhed to pieces, by the inroads of a diviner Life and Nature. This, in the Leading of that Life which hath broken it, and in the ſhinings of the Light eternal upon it, and into it, may be enabled to take up the Croſs to the natural part, and to die that Death with Chriſt, which preſerves from the ſecond Death, with the miſery thereof.</p>
               <p>Happy is he who knows and hearkens to the Perſwaſions of Gods Spirit, who is born of God, and taught to wait upon him and worſhip him in Spirit, who receives his Religion from the Light of Faith, into the renewed Nature and Mind, and not from the Reaſon of Man into the natural
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152237:20"/>
underſtanding, which is eaſily corrupted, and cannot be kept pure, but alone by the indwelling of the Principle of Eternal Life in it.</p>
               <p>For though ſuch may ſuffer very deeply in this World, from the men of this World, (as the Subjects and Servants to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Life have done in all Ages and Generations) yet their Principle will bear them out, in which God will appear to ſtrengthen and refreſh their ſpirits, and carry them up above all their Sufferings in the Patience, Meekneſs, and Faith of the Lamb: And keeping to their Principle, they cannot be overcome, but muſt either live or die Conquerors, according to the will and good pleaſure of Him who order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and diſpoſeth of all things well, and bringeth good out of every evil, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of all the Powers of Darkneſs. And he that overcometh (whether by life or death) in the Lamb's Spirit, ſhall wear the Lamb's Crown, and ſit down in that perfect Reſt in the Kingdom of the Father, which will give the hearts of all his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren full Satisfaction. In which aſſured hope (Life ſtirring in our boſoms, and quickning our hearts with Love unto our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152237:21"/>
God, and Zeal for his Truth) we can free<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly give up all that is near and dear unto u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in this World, and lay down our heads i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inward Peace, in the midſt of the greateſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> outward Perſecution and Trouble. <hi>Eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo, O Lord, thy Will be done concerning the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Generation of thy People, whom thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gotten to thy Self, and brought forth by thy mighty Power, to teſtifie to thy Truth in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſent day: Diſpoſe of them as it pleaſeth Thee, and let not their Faith in thee, nor thy Faithfulneſs to them fail, but let them be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Praiſe to thy Name throughout all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and tendered by Thee as the Firſt-fruits of thine Appearance, in the Glorious Light of the Everlaſting Day, after this great, long, thick and dark Night of Apoſtacy from the Life and Spirit of the Apoſtles, which hath ſo long eclipſed and covered the brightneſs of thy Beauty from the ſight of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iſaac Pennington.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="continuation_of_text">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152237:21"/>
            <head>A Declaration to all the World of our Faith, and what we believe, who are called <hi>Quakers. ALSO,</hi> What Miniſters and Magiſtrates we own, and what, and whom we deny.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning God, Chriſt, and the Spirit, thus we believe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, That there is only one true God, who is a Spirit, and his Preſence fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Heaven and Earth; he is Eternal and Everlaſting, the Creator and Preſerver of all things; That Heaven and Earth and all things therein, by him were framed and brought forth, and all things remain unto
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152237:22"/>
this day by his Power, and whatſoever h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> willeth in Heaven and Earth, he brings to paſs by his Word and Power.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That this God onely is, and ought to be feared, loved, obeyed and worſhipped by all Creatures, and no other thing beſides him in Heaven and Earth: and we believe that his Worſhip, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Fear, and Love is to be given in Spirit, even in what his own Spirit moveth and leadeth his people unto.</p>
               <p>And we believe his True Worſhip requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and accepted of him, is not by the tradition of men in outward obſervances <hi>or ſet dayes, or places,</hi> but he is worſhippe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only in <hi>Spirit and Truth,</hi> without reſpect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times, places or things: and that none ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worſhip him in Righteouſneſs but his Chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, who are born of his Spirit, and are le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and guided thereby.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That this God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven his Son Chriſt Jeſus, into the World a free Gift unto the whole World, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every man that cometh into the World i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lighted by him, that <hi>every man may believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we believe, That he is given int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the World, and no Nation, Country o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152237:22"/>
People excepted, but to all mankind he is given of God, and hath enlightened them; And every man through the world that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieveth in, and receiveth Chriſt, <hi>who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Wiſdom and Power of the Father,</hi> ſhall be ſaved with eternal Salvation; <hi>And eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y one that believeth not in him ſhall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and ſhall poſſeſs everlaſting miſery.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That <hi>Salvation, Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and <hi>Sanctification,</hi> is onely in Him, wrought by him and no other, for <hi>there is no other Name given under Heaven,</hi> but Him alone, by which Salvation is: and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieve all that receive him, and believe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n him are reconciled to God, and are made alive to God, to live to him in all things, and do receive the forgiveneſs of Sins, and are ſet free from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and from the body of Sin and Death, and have the witneſs of the Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n them, and the Spirit of the Father they have received, and it witneſſeth in them of the Father and of the Son, and of the things that belong to their peace; and it is the Earneſt of the Inheritance, and the Seal of the Promiſe of Eternal Life; and by it are the deep things of God revealed to mankind; and by it the Father and the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152237:23"/>
Son dwell in the Saints; and by it they have fellowſhip one with another; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Father, Son and Spirit are one: And thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we faithfully believe.</p>
               <p>Again, concerning Chriſt, we believe, That he is one with the Father, <hi>and wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with the Father before the World was;</hi> and what the Father worketh, is by the Son, for he is the Arm of Gods Salvation, and the very Power and Wiſdom of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; and <hi>was, is, and is to come, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we believe, That all the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gave Teſtimony of him, and that he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made manifeſt in <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did the Work of the Father, and was perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuted of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and was crucified by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Enemies, <hi>and that he was buried, and roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> again, according to the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we believe, He is now aſcende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on high, and exalted at the right hand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Father for evermore; and that he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> glorified with the ſame Glory that he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before the World was; <hi>and that even th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſame that came down from Heaven, is aſcende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> up to Heaven; and the ſame that deſcended, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he that aſcended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152237:23"/>And we believe, <hi>Even he that was dead, is alive, and lives for evermore; and that he cometh, and ſhall come again to judge the whole World with Righteouſneſs, and all People with Equity; and ſhall give to every man accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his deeds at the Day of Judgment, when all ſhall ariſe to Condemnation or Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he that hath done good ſhall receive Life, and he that hath done evil, everlaſting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we believe, He is to be waited for in Spirit, to be known after the Spirit, as he was before the world was, and that is the knowledge unto Eternal Life; which all that believe in him do receive; and he ſubdues Death, and deſtroys him that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he power of it, and reſtoreth from Death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Life, and quickneth by his Spirit all that the Father hath given him; and we believe ſuch he juſtifieth and ſanctifieth, and ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re taught of him: but he condemns all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat believes not, and continue in unbelief, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd are not taught of him. And this we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aithfully believe.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That unto all People <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the face of the whole Earth, is a time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd day of Viſitation given, that they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eturn and be ſaved by Jeſus Chriſt, who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152237:24"/>
is given of the Father to call the worſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men to repentance; and the moſt ungod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Sinners are convinced by him of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ungodly deeds, <hi>that they might believe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be converted, and ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we believe, Herein is the Love o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God manifeſted to all mankind; <hi>and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> none are ſhut out by him before they were bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> into the World;</hi> but unto all men is a Viſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion given, and they that periſh, it is becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they do not believe in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and <hi>Deſtruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on is of a mans ſelf,</hi> but <hi>Salvation is of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> through believing in his Son, who tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> away Sin, and reneweth into his own Imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that they may become Heirs with him.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That there is a Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Eternal Glory, and an Inheritance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eternal Life to be injoyed for evermore b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all that believe and are choſen of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And that there is an Everlaſting Miſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Deſtruction to be poſſeſſed by all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> believe not, but continues in the ſtate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Reprobation,</hi> and are not changed from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wayes of Sin and Death, but walk after t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ways of their own hearts luſts, fulfillin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the will of the Fleſh, in the evil of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> world, and follows not Chriſt the Ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the world, that they may be ſaved; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152237:24"/>
we believe upon all ſuch the wrath of God abideth, and that they have no part in the Inheritance of God. And we believe that it is only he that is born again of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and that walks after the Spirit, who is changed <hi>from Death to Life,</hi> and who is redeemed out of the World and all its wayes; ſuch only muſt inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and they onely have right thereunto, and none beſides; even they that are waſhed and cleanſed from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs by the Blood of Jeſus, by which their Sins are remitted: For his Blood cleanſeth them from all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Sin;</hi> yea, all ſuch that walk and abide in the Light which Jeſus Chriſt hath enlightned the World withal.</p>
               <p>And we believe that the Saints upon Earth may receive forgiveneſs of Sins, and may be perfectly freed from the body of Sin and Death, and in Chriſt may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and without Sin, and may have Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over all Temptations by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And we believe every Saint that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God ought to preſs after Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to overcome the Devil and all his Temptations upon Earth; and we believe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152237:25"/>
they that faithfully wait for it, ſhall obtai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, and ſhall be preſented without ſin in the Image of the Father; and ſuch wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are in Covenant with God, and their Sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are blotted out, and remembred no more for they ceaſe to commit Sin, being born o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Seed of God.</p>
               <p>And we believe the Goſpel of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the Power of God unto Salvation,</hi> and that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought to be preached <hi>freely unto all Peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and Chriſt to be held forth to all Mankin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Miniſtry ſent of him.</p>
               <p>And we believe this Miniſtry is receive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, and all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that receive it, are lawfully called to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſtry, and they may preach the Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſt freely, as they have received <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> freely; and this Miniſtry is not of Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but of God, and is made powerfull to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> converting of Sinners, and to the bringin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of People to God, and to the knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his Wayes. And we do not believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that any man is a Miniſter of Chriſt wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, or that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpel can be received by natural learnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or education.</p>
               <p>And we believe ſuch as preach for <hi>hire</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152237:25"/>
and hath hire for Preaching, are not the lawfully called Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt; ſuch as are proud, and high-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and covetous men, who do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the People at all; ſuch as have run, and never were ſent of Chriſt, who calleth by his Spirit into the Work of the Miniſtry; and as every one hath received the Gift of that Spirit, ſo he may adminiſter to others.</p>
               <p>Concerning Rulers and Governours, we believe, That there ought to be Rulers and Governours in every Nation, City, Country, or Town, and they ought to be ſuch men as fear God, and hate every evil way, <hi>who will judge for God, and not for man,</hi> and will judge Righteouſly, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually and Juſtly, and will give true and ſound Judgement unto all men, without bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, or reſpect of perſons; not regarding the Rich above the Poor, but being <hi>a praiſe unto all that do well,</hi> and <hi>a terror to all Evil-doers</hi> whatſoever, having knowledge in the pure Law of God, and themſelves continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally exerciſed therein.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That every Law of man ought to be grounded upon the Law of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152237:26"/>
God, pure Reaſon and Equity being th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Foundation thereof, that Gods Witneſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every man may anſwer to it; and the Law ought to be known unto all People, befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tranſgreſſion be charged or puniſhed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any man.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That every Tranſgre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion ought to be puniſhed according to it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nature; and that the puniſhment excee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not the greatneſs of the Tranſgreſſion; ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ought any Tranſgreſſor to eſcape u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puniſhed: neither ought any, upon fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuſpition or jealouſies, be cauſed to ſuffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without the Teſtimony of true men, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Confeſſion of the Party.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That the Executors o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Law ought to be Juſt men, and not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven to Pride, Drunkenneſs, or any othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Evil whatſoever.</p>
               <p>And we believe, That all Governou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Rulers ought to be accountable to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> People, and to the next ſucceeding Ruler for all their actions which may be enquire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into upon occaſion; and that the chiefe of the Rulers be ſubject under the Law and puniſhable by it if they be tranſgre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſors, as well as the pooreſt of the Peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thus true Judgment and Juſtice wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152237:26"/>
be brought forth in the Earth, and all that do well will have praiſe, and live in Reſt and Peace, that all Evil-doers whatſoever my ſtand in awe, and be afraid of God, and Juſt men, and the execution of good Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concerning Religion, we believe, That it is only the Spirit of the Lord that makes men truly Religious; and no man ought to be compelled to, or from any exerciſe or practiſe in Religion, by any outward Law or Power, but every man ought to be left free, as the Lord ſhall perſwade his own mind, in doing, or leaving undone this or the other practice in Religion; and every man of what profeſſion in Religion ſoever, ought to be protected in peace; provided himſelf be a man of peace, not ſeeking the wrong of any mans Perſon or Eſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And we believe, That to reprove falſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and unſound Doctrines and Principles, ſeeking to convince them that oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by Exhortation or ſharp Reproof, by word or writing, ought not to be counted a breach of the Peace; or to ſtrive about the things of the Kingdom of God, by men of contrary minds or judgments, this ought not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152237:27"/>
to be puniſhed by the Magiſtrates and their Laws: for we believe that the outward Laws and Powers of the Earth are only to preſerve mens Perſons and Eſtates, and not to preſerve men in Opinions; neither ought the Laws of the Nation to be laid upon mens Conſciences to bind them to, or from ſuch a Judgment or Practice in Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And we believe, That Chriſt is, and ought only to be Lord and Exerciſer of mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and his Spirit muſt only lead into al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And we believe, That Obedience and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection in the Lord belongs to Superiors, and that Subjects ought to obey them [in the Lord] that have rule over them: and that Children ought to obey their Parents, and Wives their Huſbands, and Servants their Maſters in all things, which is according to God, which ſtand in the exerciſe of a pure Conſcience towards God: But where Rulers, Parents, or Maſters, or any other, command or require Subjection in any thing which is contrary to God, or not according to him, in ſuch caſes all People are free, and ought to obey God rather then man: and we believe, that herein God will juſtifie them, being guided and led by his Spirt in all that which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152237:27"/>
is good, and out of all that which is evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, We believe concerning <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation;</hi> That there is a ſtate of <hi>Election,</hi> and a ſtate of <hi>Reprobation;</hi> a ſtate choſen of God, and a ſtate rejected of God; and that all mankind are in one of theſe ſtates: all that are elected are elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chriſt, and all that are out of him, are in the ſtate <hi>Reprobate,</hi> bringing forth fruits of Death and Darkneſs, <hi>being Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath and Diſobedience,</hi> in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienation</hi> and <hi>Separation from God,</hi> in the Tranſgreſſion unreconciled to God, the Enmity ruling in the heart, being in the Fall, and not reſtored to God again, but ignorant of his Power and Wiſdom, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the underſtanding darkened, that they cannot ſee nor perceive the things that are Eternal:</hi> And in this condition his beſt Works are Sin, and whatſoever he doth, he cannot be accepted with God, for he is dead to God, and alive to all Evil, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth all his Works out of that ground which is curſed. This is the condition of all mankind upon the face of the Earth in the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> and this is the ſtate of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation,</hi> and all that abide herein are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152237:28"/>
of God, and ſhall never inherit eternal Life, but go into Perdition; yet have all ſuch a day of Viſitation, that they may return out of the ſtate of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation,</hi> but hating knowledge, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Love of God, they continue in the ſtate <hi>Reprobate, and the Wrath of God abides upon them;</hi> but they that are choſen of God are delivered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom Wrath, for they believe in the Light, and become <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Light,</hi> and are renewed in mind and heart, and receive the love of the Father, and become planted into Chriſt, the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> and are choſen in him to bring forth fruit unto the Father, and all their Fruit ſpringeth from that ground which is bleſſed; for they are led by the Spirit of the Father, and ſuch are in the ſtate of <hi>Election,</hi> who are made Heirs with Chriſt of the everlaſting Inheritance that never fades away: And this we faithfully believe, that Mercy is not ſhewed to the Reprobate, nor Judgment to them that are choſen of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this is to go abroad into the World, that all People may underſtand what we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and what we have received of God: And they that believe this, and walk therein
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152237:28"/>
by the Spirit of the Father, ſhall be ſaved; but they that believe not, but are diſobedient to the Truth, ſhall be condemned becauſe they do not believe. Much more might be written; but, in ſhort, this is given forth by one that hath believed and received the knowledge of theſe things from God: A Friend unto all People.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Edward Burrough.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To all that ſay we (whom the World do in ſcorn call <hi>Quakers)</hi> do deny Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Magiſtrates, Theſe things I write unto you, to give you, in ſhort, an underſtanding, what Miniſters and Magiſtrates we own, and what, and whom we deny.</head>
               <p n="1">1. SUch Miniſters as are made by God, who are ſanctified by his Word and Power, who have freely received per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Gifts from God, and ſo by the Spirit and Power of God are ſent forth into the world, to turn the People from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152237:29"/>
the Power of God; who freely miniſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto others, without coveting any man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gold, or Silver, or Apparel; not ſeeking theirs, but them: Warning every ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and teaching every man in all Wiſdom that they may preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus: Such as miniſter from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit, and have the Word of God abiding in them, who are never unprovided, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at all times and ſeaſons, and in all places do ſpeak and declare the Truth, as they are moved and inſtructed, and as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth doth give them utterance; Such Miniſters we own, and have in great eſteem <hi>for their works ſake, Gal.</hi> 1.1, 12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.7, 8, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Matth</hi> 10.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.33 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 1.27, 28, 29. 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 3.6. <hi>John</hi> 15.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>John</hi> 4.10, 14. and 7.38, 39. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.2, 3. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p>But ſuch as are brought up at Schools and Colledges, and ſo made Miniſters by the will of man, who have not freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived perfect gifts from God for perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Saints, but denies <hi>Perfection,</hi> and ſo denies the Miniſters work, neither do miniſter freely, but ſeek for gain from
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152237:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Quarters, and will not preach with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a price; who are not ſanctified by the Word of God, but plead for a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in Sin while people walk upon the Earth: Such as miniſter from the Letter, and not from the Spirit; who cannot preach except they have time to ſtudy, and ſo by their induſtry provide themſelves, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not provided of the Lord (ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is of Works, and not the Free Gift from God) ſuch cannot profit people, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead them captive in an empty and dead Form, <hi>alwayes learning, but never able to come to the true knowledge of God:</hi> ſuch cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Miniſters we do deny, and turn from them, and teſtifie againſt them, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y men of God formerly did; read <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19, 20, 26, 27, 28, 29. and <hi>chap</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.22, 30, 31, 32, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19. <hi>Jude</hi> 11. <hi>John</hi> 8.24. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.15, 16, 17. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.9. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6, 10, 11. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such Magiſtrates who rule for God, who be men of Truth, <hi>fearing God and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Covetouſneſs:</hi> who execute true Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152237:30"/>
and Judgment in the Earth without partiality, not reſpecting the perſons of the Rich, nor deſpiſing the perſons of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Poor, but in Truth and Equity giving to every one his due and portion according to the Law of Equity; who neither ſees nor receive honour from men, but ſee the honour that comes from God onely who are a <hi>terror to Evil-doers,</hi> but <hi>a prai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to them that do well;</hi> ſuch Magiſtrates w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own, and in the Lord honour, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.18, 19, 20. <hi>John</hi> 5.41, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4.</p>
               <p>But ſuch Magiſtrates who be proud an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lofty; who rule not for God, but for them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves; who love the praiſe of men, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judge for gifts and rewards, and love mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney which is the root of all evil; who re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect the rich in their gay cloathing, abov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the poor in vile rayment; who ſeek an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> receive honour of men (and if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not honoured with that which they ſee for, <hi>turns Judgment backward, that Equi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cannot enter</hi>) ſuch as be wrathfull and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licious cannot rule for God, ſuch are e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>couragers of Vice and Wickedneſs, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> turn their Sword backward againſt the U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right and Innocent, who reprove ſin i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:152237:30"/>
the gate; ſuch Magiſtrates we do deny and teſtifie againſt: for, <hi>when the Wicked bear rule, the Righteous mourn,</hi> and the Evil-doers rejoyce over them, and mock and reproach them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1, 23. <hi>John</hi> 6.43. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 9. <hi>John</hi> 5.44. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.13, 14, 15. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa.</hi> 29.21. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.2.</p>
               <p>Such as live in Pride and Pleaſures, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollow ungodly Luſts, and wicked practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, deny God, though in words they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rofeſs him; even ſo, all ſuch as do evil, who follows Drunkenneſs, Oaths, Games, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain Sports and Pleaſures, and ſuch like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngodly actions, do deny, diſgrace and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reatly diſhonour both Miniſters and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtrates, though in words they may own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, and bow the Hat and Knee, and give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttering Titles unto them; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Paſm</hi> 15. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. <hi>James</hi> 1.25. <hi>Job</hi> 32.1, 22.</p>
               <p>To walk Soberly, Righteouſly, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g Juſtly according as the Grace of God, which brings Salvation, doth teach an di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect, is a ſweet ſavour to the Lord, and true owning, and in the Lord honouring, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue Miniſters and Magiſtrates, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152237:31"/>
8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>Rom</hi> 13.3.</p>
               <p>But to walk looſly and prophanely, do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing wicked and unjuſt actions, turning th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Grace of God into wantonneſs; Suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are an ill ſavour to God, and denies an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſhonours True Miniſters and Magiſtrate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>James</hi> 3.14, 15, 16. <hi>Jude</hi> 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>True Honour doth not conſiſt in bow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the Hat and Knee, and ſuch like thing (for that is the honour below, which me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeek and receive one of another, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is in the unbelief,) but in the obedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Magiſtrates juſt Commands, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are a Terror to wickedneſs, but a Praiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them that do well: For the Law w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not made for the Righteous, who fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, and live uprightly, but for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lawleſs, who are out of Gods Fear, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> live wickedly, caſting the Law of God be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hind their backs, <hi>John</hi> 5.44. <hi>Romans</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3, 4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 17.</p>
               <p>So this may certifie all whom this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come unto, that we do not deny Miniſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor Magiſtrates, who are made and or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dained by God, but honour them in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152237:31"/>
Lord; let our Lives and Converſations, and That of God in all your Conſciences judge; for if all were brought into our Life, the Magiſtrate ſhould live at peace: and ſo as the eyes of your underſtandings come to be opened with true Light, you will ſee that thoſe who live Soberly and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do own and honour Miniſters and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrates, though they cannot for conſcience ſake reſpect their perſons, nor give them flattering Titles, as <hi>your Highneſs, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, your Worſhip,</hi> and ſuch like, for ſuch belong to God: For, Chriſt Jeſus ſaid, <hi>I receive not honour from man:</hi> and ſaith he, <hi>How can you believe, that receive honour one of another, and ſeeks not the honour that comes from God only?</hi> Gal. 1.11, 12. Rom. 13.1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.18, 19. John 1.9. Jam. 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 9. John 5.44.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Read with underſtanding, prove all things hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 
                     <bibl>1 Theſ. 5.21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. Parker.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152237:32"/>
               <head>To all that want Peace with God; T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Sheep every where not brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> home; To the thirty breathing Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to the Seed, though in Captivi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty among, and in the midſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Profeſſors; Greetings of Love, Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, and Peace from God the Father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Living.</head>
               <p>VVHere the Bowels are not ſhut up nor the Heart darkened; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where that doth not bear rule which ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth the ear, and cloſeth the eye; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where prejudice and Rebellion again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Light,</hi> with the wiſdom of the fleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through that knowledge which puffeth u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath not wholly eaten up, devoured, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over, and wholly overcome that Tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Principle, which once moved in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart, towards that <hi>Beeing</hi> of the Livin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Subſtance, there may my words ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> entrance; and unto ſuch who feel th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which breaths to God, and who are wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling to be ſatisfied concerning the Livin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:152237:32"/>
Truth of his Son, and who would receive the Truth if they knew it, and do yet more deſire after the Power of God, then all the temporal things that are ſeen; and who are yet come no further than the <hi>reading of the Law, the Prieſts, Tythes,</hi> and that Religion that makes nothing perfect: and who are come no further then the outward <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>Shadow,</hi> or <hi>Figure,</hi> or ſuch things which are to be left behind, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6. or who are come no further than the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> or the <hi>Death,</hi> and ſo not yet ſaved by his <hi>Life,</hi> nor drunk of that which ſaveth, and is to cleanſe from all that which ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth from God; after whom, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of his Love immortal, whoſoever truly deſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, and is willing to receive the Power of his Life, and come into Covenant with the Lord.</p>
               <p>Such may lend me an ear a little, and you are them who may receive ſome bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit hereby; for behold I write in plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the things of God, my heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enlarged with abundance of his Peace, in which there is good will towards men, that you might come to draw near to the <hi>Witneſs,</hi> the teſtimony whereof is within the Vail, which Vail is over the heart,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152237:33"/>
2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. and is not done away but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you come to be in him, who is <hi>given for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Witneſs,</hi> Iſaiah 55.4. by believing in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Light, <hi>John</hi> 12.36. and ſo to have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Witneſs in you, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. and you t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be in it; and that you may come to part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipate of Gods indwellings, and feel th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Oyl which will laſt for ever; therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> proceed thus:</p>
               <p>How can I but look back a little, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an eye of pitty over thoſe, who yet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where once I was when the Darkneſs w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over the Earth, and the cloud of Erro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> compaſſed me as well as others; ſurely, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cannot now be unmindfull of them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are yet <hi>loſt,</hi> as not to have compaſſion u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the <hi>Out-caſts of Iſrael,</hi> or to conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from them theſe things of ſo great concer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, but rather, as the Lord of my Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath opened to me, I will reach forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hand towards the weak, and utter my voi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Priſoner of hope, and ſhew unto t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meek in the Earth, how the inviſible G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath led his Seed, and is leading his Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant through, and out of the variety <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> things, unto the <hi>One Thing</hi> it ſelf, fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whence the various Things, Gifts and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtrations do come.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:152237:33"/>Now, that which is chiefly in my heart to write, for the Seeds ſake, is,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Something concerning the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Moſes</hi> (when he was upon the Earth.)</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Concerning the Miniſtration of Chriſt</hi> (whilſt he was upon Earth)</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and chiefly, <hi>Concerning the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Firſt, Concerning <hi>Moſes</hi> Miniſtration, (when he was upon Earth) which was to laſt till <hi>Shilo</hi> came, or until the time of Reformation.</head>
                  <p>AS concerning <hi>Moſes</hi>'s <hi>Miniſtration,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Law, Condemnation,</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> with the Prieſts Offering, and worldly Sanctuary, and an outward Tabernacle, and daily Offerings for ſin, and Store-houſes for the Levites, Strangers, Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Widows, having the Ark of the Teſtimony within the Vail, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-Seat covered, and the Golden Pot, and the People to ſeek the Law at the Prieſts mouth, whereby their knowledge is preſerved, and many profit much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152237:34"/>
and come day by day, and year <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> year unto that which they eſteem a pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Holy Worſhip, and Ordinances of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> And notwithſtanding the Prieſts of <hi>Moſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Law were made by the Law of God, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that Prieſthood changeth, and the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> changeth, and the very glory of all thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paſſeth away; for this did once ſeem glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious unto me, and many more which on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diſcovered ſin, though it made nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perfect, and with much delight was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reading of the Law and the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hearkened unto, and the daily Confeſſion of Sin (but the Vail is over the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whilſt. <hi>Moſes</hi> is preached) and Sacrifice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Morning and Evening, with the long Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which the Comers thereunto were not at all thereby made perfect, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Conſcience; though it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Shadow of good things to come, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the glory thereof comes to be done away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then how much more will the very glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the moſt glorious appearance of that Miniſtry periſh, and be done away, which cometh ſhort of this, and hath not ſo much as the image of this, which was a Shaddow? O weak and beggerly things that are found among thoſe Prieſts now,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152237:34"/>
and their Followers, who come ſhort of <hi>Moſe</hi>'s Miniſtry! for he directed them to Chriſt, the Subſtance, and ſo his Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion comes to be done away, as Chriſt comes to be received: for <hi>Moſes</hi> did not ſeek to uphold his Prieſts, or Law, or Tythes, or any thing elſe, when Chriſt ſhould come, who is the end of the Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut did write of him; and notwithſtanding his Miniſtry and Prieſts, he ſaid, <hi>He that would not hearken unto him, ſhould be cut off;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>The Lord will raiſe up,</hi> (mark the words) <hi>raiſe up; the Lord ſhall raiſe up a Prophet;</hi> and when the Prophet was come, he ſaid, <hi>I am the Light, and I am meek and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow in heart;</hi> and this is to be raiſed up which is meek; <hi>for to them that ſate in darkneſs, Light hath ſprung up:</hi> And the Soul that hearkneth not to the Prophet which <hi>ſprings up</hi> ſhall be cut off, for Truth <hi>ſpringeth up</hi> out of the Earth, <hi>and Chriſt is the Truth;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>I am the Light,</hi> which is the horn of Salvation that God <hi>raiſed up</hi> to be a <hi>Light</hi> to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and is the Salvation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and ſo the ſoul is to hearken to that which God raiſed up, and that is it which condemneth Sin (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it) who is like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152237:35"/>
                     <hi>diſcovers Sin,</hi> and ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> directed un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Chriſt (who puts away the Sin:) and <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſaid of the glory of <hi>Moſe</hi>'s Miniſtration that it was no glory, in reſpect of the glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Miniſtration of the Spirit; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> glorious Miniſtry of the Spirit was rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved, after he who had a body prepared, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuffered the crucifying of his body, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Prophets ſearched diligently to ſee the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry that was to be after the Sufferings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11.</p>
                  <p>But the thing intended, That <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> when he was upon Earth, directed unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and gave commandment <hi>that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhould hearken unto him</hi> (who ſaid, <hi>I am th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Light) and this is one Tittle of the Law, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Light be hearkened unto,</hi> who is the <hi>end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Law,</hi> and the <hi>Subſtance;</hi> and he that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fendeth herein, is guilty of all; and this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that in which all the large Miniſtrations o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> is included, that, <hi>Chriſt the Light,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>true Prophet</hi> be <hi>hearkened unto</hi> and <hi>obeye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> that by <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>obeying</hi> his voice (or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> word in the heart) they might come from under the Law, and the Prieſts, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which <hi>waxeth old,</hi> unto the <hi>Life</hi> &amp; <hi>Obedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of him who abides a <hi>Prieſt for ever,</hi> even th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Lord of that Glory,</hi> which laſteth for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:152237:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Concerning CHRIST, and his Miniſtration, when he was upon Earth) and his Work which he finiſhed.</head>
                  <p>ANd when he cometh, which <hi>Moſes</hi> commandeth <hi>to hearken unto,</hi> even <hi>Chriſt, the true Prophet, the Light of the World, the Living Miniſter, the end of the Law,</hi> who had a body prepared to do the Will of the Father, which was in him, <hi>the Man CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Follow me;</hi> and he took up his Croſs and paſſed through the <hi>Death</hi> and the <hi>Vail,</hi> and ſo being made perfect through Sufferings, attained that glory which he had with the Father before he had a body, which body, was prepared to do the <hi>Fathers Will;</hi> whoſe Will was, that all men ſhould be ſaved; therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> taſted death for every man, and roſe again for the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of thoſe that believe in him, who ſaid, <hi>I am the Light,</hi> and is ſate down at the right hand of God, who is a Spirit eternally in the Heavens, aſcended up out of the ſight of them which gazed after
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152237:36"/>
that body which is gone out of their ſight, even he, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Myſtery,</hi> hid from Ages and Generations, now made manifeſt <hi>to deſtroy the works of the Devil;</hi> being meek and low in heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſaith, <hi>Learn of me:</hi> Then not of the Prieſts, nor any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the Law is the <hi>Schoolma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to Chriſt;</hi> who being come, calleth one from the <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> another from going to <hi>bury the Dead,</hi> another from queſtioning and reaſoning what this man, or another ſhould do; that he might not ſtand looking out at others, but himſelf to follow the Light, ſaying, <hi>Follow thou me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thoſe that followed him when he was upon Earth, ſaw <hi>his Miracles,</hi> and heard <hi>his Parables,</hi> and eat of the <hi>outward Bread</hi> and were <hi>filled,</hi> (though many now eat, and are not filled) and they had his Body among them, and they came to the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Supper, but Chriſt himſelf baptized not:</hi> and when he was upon the Earth, he ſaid, <hi>I go to the Father,</hi> and <hi>I go to prepare a place for you;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>Whither I go ye know;</hi> and he ſaid before, <hi>Follow me;</hi> and <hi>except a man deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs and follow me, he cannot be my Diſciple:</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>My Sheep hear
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152237:36"/>
my Voice, and they followed me: and he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred within the vail,</hi> (and the vail is over the heart) <hi>and was made perfect through ſufferings,</hi> and is <hi>ſate down in the Majeſty on high, glorified with God the Father; and the Father was in him,</hi> even the fulneſs of God; <hi>and that which may be known of God is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in thee;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>he had finiſhed the work the Father gave him to do,</hi> and ſo the Fathers will was accompliſhed and done, for which the body was prepared: he ſaid, <hi>Now glorifie me, Father, with the ſame glory which I had with thee from the beginning;</hi> and he that ſpake in the body abideth for ever, who ſaid, <hi>A Body haſt thou prepared me,</hi> which Body being crucified, he took up <hi>his Life again,</hi> and then thoſe that did know him three dayes before, knew him not: and he aſcended, and a cloud recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him out of the ſight of certain men, who never found him unto this day, for he remaineth out of the ſight of moſt that profeſs him, and as Lightning in the <hi>Clouds of Heaven</hi> doth he come again, and every eye ſhall ſee <hi>him that condemneth ſin:</hi> and the Kingdom of Heaven <hi>is within you,</hi> and yet the <hi>blind</hi> cannot <hi>ſee,</hi> nor the <hi>deaf hear.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:152237:37"/>And this was he that <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded to <hi>hear,</hi> who ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He that is <hi>with you</hi> ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be <hi>in you,</hi> and he that was <hi>with</hi> or <hi>without</hi> was to go away; and that which was to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> received <hi>within,</hi> he ſaid ſhould <hi>abide wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them for ever,</hi> and the Spirit of Truth wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to <hi>lead into all Truth:</hi> for, though the body w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s prepared to do Gods Will, yet they by it were not led into all Truth, but ſome times underſtood it not, though he ſpake <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life;</hi> and moreover, they wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> away, and ſome fled from the Truth, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> denied him that was the Truth: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo ſuch as have got a profeſſion of the <hi>Truth without them,</hi> and not the Spirit <hi>within</hi> to lead <hi>into all Truth,</hi> ſuch fly in the day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tryal, from that Truth they profeſs; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſome deny it rather then ſuffer with, or fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it; and herein them called <hi>Baptiſts</hi> alſo have not come ſhort; and ſome of them have bowed to the Beaſt; and ſo it is with many who profeſs Chriſt, and Truth <hi>with out them,</hi> even as with thoſe who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not the <hi>Parables,</hi> neither could caſt out the <hi>unclean Spirits;</hi> ſo that Chriſt was and is grieved, when he hath been ſo long <hi>with,</hi> and profeſſed and followed <hi>without,</hi> and yet not come to that Faith which pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152237:37"/>
the heart, whereby to caſt out the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean <hi>within,</hi> as thou mayſt read in thy ſelf.</p>
                  <p>And therefore Chriſt, when he was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, did often ſpeak unto them, of what was yet to come; and I do ſeldom read, or take notice, that he did ſo often preach and repeat any one thing unto them, as that of the Spirit to come, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>it,</hi> (mark, the Spirit,) <hi>would lead into all Truth;</hi> and ſeeing their weakneſs and unbelief, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.14. he by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repetition thereof, did (as it were) the more chiefly to engage their hearts to wait for, and ſeek after the incomes of that which ſhould comfort them, and abide with them, when his Body was gone from them whither they could not come; and to this one thing doth he direct them in various expreſſions, as of his going to the Father, and coming again, and ſaith he, <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, even the Spirit of Truth, whom the World cannot receive,</hi> John 14.16. <hi>And many things Jeſus did, which if they ſhould be all written, the World might not contain the Books,</hi> John 21.25. <hi>and many things he ſpake unto them,</hi> Acts 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. and yet there was ſomenthing to come to be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152237:38"/>
waited for, and after to be received, which was more then all this; for, ſaith he, <hi>Theſe things have I ſpoken unto you, being yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with you; [but] the Comforter,</hi> &amp;c. Mark, the work, <hi>but,</hi> intimateth ſomething greater, or more then what was ſpoken to them, whilſt he was with them; for, ſaith he, <hi>He that is with you, ſhall be in you,</hi> John 14.17. and ſaid, <hi>but the Comforter, which is the holy Spirit, whom the Father will ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in my Name, he will teach you all things,</hi> (mark what that is that teacheth all things) <hi>and brings all things to your remembrance, whatſoever I have ſaid,</hi> (and ſo, that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which bringeth the words of Spirit and Life to remembrance) <hi>John</hi> 14.25, 26. and having ſpoken of other things, he ſaith again, <hi>But when the Comforter comes, even the Spirit of Truth,</hi> John 15.26. <hi>and if I go not away, the Comforter will not come but if I depart I will ſend him unto you,</hi> Joh. 16.7. <hi>And I have many things to ſay unto you, but you cannot bear them now,</hi> howbeit, <hi>when he, the Spirit of Truth is come, he will guide you into all Truth,</hi> John 16.12.13. here it may be ſeen that they who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Chriſt without,</hi> and not received the <hi>Spirit within</hi> could not bear what he
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152237:38"/>
had to ſpeak unto them; and alſo, it may be ſeen that when the Spirit <hi>was come,</hi> it would be better with them</p>
                  <p>And much more might be mentioned, how Chriſt foretold what was to come and be received, and revealed in that day, <hi>John</hi> 16.23. when the Spirit ſhould be poured forth according to the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s; all which plainly declareth, and moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſets forth, how Chriſt in his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, when he was upon Earth, did moſt chiefly direct unto the Miniſtration of the Spirit of Truth, which was then yet to come; and that they might not run to teach others (as many do now) before they had received the Spirit of Truth <hi>in themſelves,</hi> by, and with that to be led into all Truth, but might receive the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of truth in themſelves, from the Life thereof, to convert others <hi>into the ſame;</hi> therefore ſaid he further, after he was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen again, <hi>But tarry ye in the City of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem until you be endued with power from on high,</hi> Mark 24.4. ſo that though they had ſeen his body before, and had now ſeen him after his Reſurrection, yet that and all the reſt was not enough without the Power and the Spirit which was to come,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152237:39"/>
which they were to wait for. And ſo now men ſhould tarry, wait, and ſtand ſtill, to ſee the Salvation of God, and until they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Spirit, for it is the Spirit (not the body) which ſearcheth all things, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth plainly of the Father.</p>
                  <p>And by this before written in ſhort, I have a little endeavoured, to ſhew, unto the meek and ſingle-hearted, that <hi>Moſes</hi> when he was upon Earth, directed unto Chriſt; As in theſe words,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord thy God will raiſe up unto thee a Prophet from the midſt of thee, of thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, like unto me, unto him ſhall ye hearken,</hi> Deut. 18.15.</p>
                  <p>And Chriſt when he was upon Earth, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected unto the Spirit which was to come, in like words, ſaying,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe things have I ſpoken unto you, being yet preſent with you, but the Comforter, which is the holy Spirit, whom the Father will ſend in my Name, he ſhall teach you all things,</hi> John 14.25, 26.</p>
                  <p>And then, what if I did write after the manner of men, and ſay, If <hi>Moſes</hi> were now upon the Earth, and Chriſt in his own body upon the Earth, and <hi>Moſes</hi> with all his Prieſts, Tyth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and Offerings, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152237:39"/>
which diſcovers Sin, but makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing perfect, which <hi>Paul</hi> profitted much in; If he, I ſay, ſhould <hi>command and exhort all people under his Miniſtry, to go to Chriſt and hear him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if Chriſt were now upon Earth, and notwithſtanding his outward Miracles, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, Baptiſm, Supper, and Death, yet he ſhould <hi>command and exhort all</hi> that (come through the Law or Miniſtration of <hi>Moſes</hi> unto him) <hi>to look, and tarry, and wait for another Comforter,</hi> that they might receive the Spirit in them, and ſay unto them, that <hi>that ſhould teach them all things, and lead them into all Truth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then whether or no people were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue following <hi>Moſe</hi>'s <hi>Prieſts,</hi> with their Tythes and long Prayers, and ſtill be ſeeking the Law at their mouth, or <hi>to come to Chriſt,</hi> to ſeek the Goſpel? for <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf did not ſay, that they ſhould ſeek the Goſpel at the Prieſts mouth: And then, when did the Prieſts ever preach the Goſpel?</p>
                  <p>And then, whether thoſe obey not <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> who leave the Prieſts and come to Chriſt, the <hi>Light?</hi> and whether ſuch when they are come to Chriſt, ſhould alwayes
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152237:40"/>
be looking and following after his Body, Miracles Baptiſm, or Supper <hi>without them,</hi> or tarry and wait to receive the Spirit <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then, which of theſe now ſhould all people that profeſs Chriſt, be led by in theſe dayes, either <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>the Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>the Spirit of Truth?</hi> And, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch as have received, and are truly indeed led by this Spirit of Truth, and know that to be their Teacher, and follow it, and are ruled, governed, and guided by it, according to the Command of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> do not hereby obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and fulfil their Doctrine? And whether any other People or Profeſſors whatſoever do obey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but only ſuch? And whether this be not a thing of great concernment to be known and learned by all who profeſs Chriſtianity?</p>
                  <p>But why then do People follow theſe Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> any longer, which are contrary to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and alſo to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who have no Store-houſes, but ſuffer the poor to want within and without, and the Widow and the Stranger ready to periſh, and moreover devour, and can never
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152237:40"/>
have enough of the Spoil of other mens goods?</p>
                  <p>And why do others diſpute about, and talk of the Body ſo much, which they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw nor knew? And is it not better be ſilent, and know God who dwells in his People, and the Spirit of Truth, which he requires in the inward parts, and to feel after God, even the Life in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaid, they <hi>were ſaved by his Life, being before reconciled by his Death,</hi> Rom. 5.10. and until the Life came, there were many things which they were not ſaved from by his Body, for the Body was before the Death, and the Death which reconciles was paſſed through, before the Life was received again to ſave and juſtifie.</p>
                  <p>And why then are People ſo much buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about that which was before the Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation (and ſo therein much ſhort of the Life) and for outward <hi>Bread, Wine</hi> and <hi>Water;</hi> Are not theſe things which are ſeen? And are not the things that are ſeen Temporal?</p>
                  <p>But Chriſt, the true Prophet, being come, of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> did write, who is the end of the Law, and ſo the end of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152237:41"/>
that Miniſtry, whereby that is done away for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thereof; and Chriſt coming after <hi>John,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whom <hi>John</hi> bare witneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and greater, and came after him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Chriſt alſo having finiſhed that which he himſelf came to do; and likewiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo largely and often Exhorted to wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for <hi>another Comforter, even the Spirit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then what Miniſtration is it that now ſtandeth and remaineth, which is accordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> both to <hi>Moſes, Chriſt</hi> and the holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures?</hi> and what Miniſtration is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pected or waited for, but the Miniſtratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Spirit? And whether all they be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> compaſſed about with a cloud of Error, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are upholding that Miniſtry of the Law (or a worſe) which Chriſt is the end of and the Apoſtles ſaid, <hi>was done away;</hi> and likewiſe ſuch as are upholding and keeping up that which Chriſt ſaid <hi>he had finiſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> And whether the upholding of ſuch thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> now, be not quite oppoſite, both to <hi>Moſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Scriptures?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And being that <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor indeed hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> true Miniſters of the Law, <hi>are not up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Earth,</hi> neither that Body of Chriſt (which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152237:41"/>
by the Profeſſors was murthered at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi>) viſibly to be ſeen <hi>upon Earth;</hi> then what was it thoſe have to follow, who have not received the <hi>Spirit to be led by?</hi> and if they will ſay, they <hi>have the Writings of Moſes</hi> and <hi>the Word of Chriſt;</hi> I ſay, if that be all, then they that forſook and denied Chriſt had more than them; for they had the words from his own mouth, which were <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and yet they underſtood not; (and then what do thoſe underſtand who have not ſo much as they had?) therefore after he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and roſe again, he opened their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings.</p>
                  <p>And ſo, what is all their Religion worth, who are not come to the Spirit? And whether <hi>Moſes</hi> Miniſtration being ended by Chriſt, and Chriſt alſo having finiſhed his work, are not all people in the firſt place, now to wait for the Spirit, and to receive the Spirit by it, then to be led into all Truth; and ſo being firſt led into the Truth, then in the ſame Truth to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in Spirit who is a Spirit? And whether there be now any true Worſhip ſtanding which God accepteth, but only this? And whether this alone be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152237:42"/>
to <hi>Moſes, Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Scriptures?</hi> And whether all other Worſhips now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, be not contrary to this true Worſhip of God, and contrary to <hi>Moſes, Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and indeed chiefly oppoſite to the Spirit of God, whereby he is grieved? And if ſo, whether all ſuch Worſhip, Way, Practice, Performances, Duties, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances (ſo called) be not better left undone then performed, until Gods Spirit be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to guide therein?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Concerning the Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit, which abideth for ever.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MOſes</hi> and his Miniſtry were viſible, and Chriſt in the form of a Servant (and ſo like unto <hi>Moſes</hi>) was viſible, and ſo were his Miracles; and that which is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the natural eye, the carnal mind can come to profeſs and contend about; but the bleſſed eye, which God openeth with the light, cometh to ſee the one done away, and the other finiſhed by Chriſt, the Light and Life.</p>
                  <p>And the Spirit is that which firſt moved, and yet moveth, and moved unto, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152237:42"/>
led through the viſible Miniſtration; and this Spirit is inviſible, as it is written, <hi>the inviſible only wiſe God,</hi> whom no eye of fleſh hath ſeen, or can ſee; and this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving inviſible Spirit of God which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out limit or end, is that which all people ſhould be led unto, by all its outward vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible appearances, miniſtrations and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations; and this Spirit was that which gave forth and ordained the Miniſtration of the Law, which was glorious in its time, though to be done away: but how much more glorious is the Miniſtration of that Spirit of Life it ſelf, from which the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Law came, which Spirit abideth for ever. And the <hi>ſecond Adam is made a quickning Spirit;</hi> and the Spirit which is the Word, <hi>was with God,</hi> and <hi>was God,</hi> before the body of fleſh was made; and that Spirit abideth for ever, as is heard out of the Law, <hi>He ſhall abide for ever;</hi> And this is that which ever liveth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ercede.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And this for ever bleſſed inviſible Spirit was before time, and is to be when time ſhall be no more; and is without limit, an eternal lively Subſtance, giving life from it ſelf, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152237:43"/>
ſecretly covering it ſelf from the carnal part of man, not ſeen nor underſtood, but by ſuch as by its ſecret motions come to be led to ſee through that which ſhadows it forth, and by the image, form, ſhadow or figure, to diſcern the Subſtance, which is the Life, where Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality dwelleth: for in the moſt innermoſt and ſecret of all is the Life of all, being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over with that in which it lies; through which it breaking forth in any diſcovery of it ſelf, is that whereby the beholders might be drawn through the diſcovery unto it ſelf, which in the diſcovery broke forth; for the diſcovery was ſtill too ſhort of that from whence it came, and that which was diſcovered forth in any ſhadow, form, or image, was not to be idolized nor ſet up, for the very thing or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Life, from whence it proceeded; and herein hath been much miſtake, by ſuch who came not by that, which opened in the viſibles, to that from whence it came, in that to have their underſtandings opened, and thereby to be made ſenſible of that which is eternal, by it to be brought in, where its indwellings abide for ever, whoſe breaking forth in the viſible (which was to draw to that inviſible) refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſoul inviſibly, in an unexpected manner and time; but being</hi> (after) <hi>ſought for in the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152237:43"/>
viſibles (and not in the eternal) withdraws it ſelf out of the viſibles, and out of the ſight and reach of that which ſeeks it there, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that which is to live for ever with it, may come through all that which it appeared in, unto the very thing and inviſible Subſtance it ſelf, which is the Life of all, and the true Center of the living Motion which moveth of it ſelf, and gave forth all things good, as they proceeded from it, by vertue of its gradual, and various motions; and this being come, opens it ſelf in them that find it, and live therein; and this maketh Darkneſs Light before the people whoſe dwelling is with God, and the crooked comes to be made ſtreight by the thing it ſelf, and dark ſayings of old come to be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſecret things revealed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to write more plain for the ſake of the weak, of this glorious indwelling Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which in the fulneſs of time cometh forth in fleſh, laying hold of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the moſt glorious Appearance that ever was; being thus appeared; was the expreſs Image of God, who dwelleth in his People, whoſe bodies are fleſh and earthly tabernacles; but by the operation of the <hi>ſanctifying cleanſing Spirit,</hi> which the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152237:44"/>
Father ſendeth, are made fit habitations of God, and ſo Coheirs with Chriſt, and Members of his Body, Fleſh and Bones; which Spirit quickneth to God, and being thus received and obeyed, is felt to live for ever, though the ſhadowings-forth of it be done away; and this is Eternal, and never endeth, but abideth with ſuch for ever; and the Miniſtration of it is Life it ſelf to the ſoul, and more to be valued and deſired, than all that ever was ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it.</p>
                  <p>And as the Lord took of that Spirit which was upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> and put it upon his Brethren the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whereby they might rule and judge with him: ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The Father ſhall take of mine, and give it unto you,</hi> even of that Spirit of Love, Life, Power, Valour and Virtue which was upon and in him (that was like unto <hi>Moſes</hi>) is miniſtred into, and put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch as are truly his Brethren and Friends, whereby, with him, they (thus gifted, ſanctified and qualified) judge the World: <hi>for all Judgment is committed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Son,</hi> and of that which the Son hath (and is committed to him) doth the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give unto his Members, and ſo from
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152237:44"/>
Chriſt the Head they come to receive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the World, and its Way, Worſhip, and Faſhions, and over unclean ſpirits. And that is an unclean ſpirit which will lead in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any ſin, and it is an unclean ſpirit in which ſin ſtandeth, and which pleadeth for the continuance, and upholding of that which is unclean; and that is of the world, which the Saints judge.</p>
                  <p>And as thoſe Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (who were of the Church in the Wilderneſs) were not made fit <hi>to Judge or Rule in outward matters</hi> by all the writings and words of the Law (though received by diſpoſition of Angels) until the Lord himſelf took of that Spirit which was upon <hi>Moſes</hi> and put upon them.</p>
                  <p>So thoſe that profeſs to be Elders in the Church now, or any other perſon whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, are much leſs made fit to <hi>Rule or Judge in ſpiritual matters,</hi> by all the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and profeſſing <hi>Moſes</hi> Writings, and Chriſt's Words, and the reſt of the holy Scriptures (though they were given by the inſpiration of God) until the Lord take of that Spirit which was upon, and in Chriſt, (who is like unto <hi>Moſes</hi>) and give unto, and pour it upon, and miniſter it <hi>in</hi> unto
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152237:45"/>
them. And this is done in Gods way (which is ſecret) and time (which is in his own hand) to thoſe whom he accounteth worthy thus to honour, and who truly wait for it, as a wayfering man for a reſting place, and as a Captive for deliverance.</p>
                  <p>And though Chriſt (after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) ſaid, <hi>All Power in Heaven and in Earth is given unto me, Go ye therefore and teach,</hi> yet they were to tarry until they had the power in themſelves; and when that was come which they were to tarry and wait for, then with that they went, and ſo taught the Nations, from the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feeling of that which taught them how to teach, and all things elſe, when the ſame Spirit and Power was upon them, which was before committed unto him; and ſo the coming forth of it from him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and filling them therewith, was to them in that work of the Miniſtry moſt effectual: like as the Vertue going forth of Chriſt healed the woman; ſo the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Vertue of the holy Spirit, coming forth from Chriſt, being ſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and received by the Diſciples (who with much deſire waited for that) impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered them to do that which before they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152237:45"/>
were commanded to do, after they were endued with Power (or had the Power in them) and ſo what they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commanded to do, they were to wait to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Power in themſelves from God to perform; and Chriſt did intend to give them power to do that which he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And as he commanded them to go and teach, he alſo required them to tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (and ſo not to go) until they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived power ſo to do; and ſo it was the Power of the holy Ghoſt in them, which made them Miniſters, and theſe were, and ſuch are, truly Ordained Miniſters: And after they had received Power from on high, even the Spirit (or Life) of Truth, and were filled therewith, and ſo had it in them, then they went to do that which was commanded them, then they went to teach the Nations, and converted tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and turned ſinners, and brought ſouls to God, and then they were called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and then were People brought to be of the True Church which Chriſt buildeth, upon that which fleſh and blood revealeth not.</p>
                  <p>And this is the entrance into the Church in God, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>the receiving of the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152237:46"/>
Spirit,</hi> and in this God is worſhiped, and not elſe, for this hath excluded all other Worſhip; and theſe only are the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, who come in thus by the door<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is Chriſt, the Light and Spirit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Truth, ſent into the heart from God.</p>
                  <p>And if all the prudent learned Divine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (ſo called) in <hi>Europe,</hi> or all, or any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the wiſeſt Orthodox men (ſo called) i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any other quarter of the whole World, can prove by the (Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament) any other true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God (who is a Spirit) now exta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> among men, and to be performed (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially among them called Chriſtians) with acceptance to God, but only that which the Spirit of Truth leadeth ſuch unto as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; then let them bring it forth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> we may ſee it, and prove it by plain u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable truth of Scripture; or otherwiſe I ſhall look upon their proofs, words, wayes, actions, practiſes, performances, duties, and ſeveral Worſhips, as things of no value.</p>
                  <p>Or if there be any other entrance into the true Worſhip of God then this Spirit that God ſendeth (or the Light which leadeth to it) or if there be any other Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152237:46"/>
which God doth, or will accept to be after this, ſpoken or propheſied of in the Scriptures of Truth, whereby this ſhall ever be done away, or ended, from being the true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> only, and alone Worſhip of God, whilſt men have a being upon Earth, then let the wiſeſt of the ſons of men bring it forth, and produce their ſtrong Reaſons therein, that we may plead together, and that the entrance into, and the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it ſelf of the onely true inviſible God, may be declared over all the World, for the ſatisfaction of every tender heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this.</p>
                  <p>For this I am ſatisfied in, that Chriſt Jeſus (who is the end of the Law, and who finiſhed his work, when he was upon the Earth) is made a quickning Spirit, and is the Way and Truth of Life, which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the Worſhip of God, and he is the beginning and the end, and he leadeth to the beginning of Gods Worſhip, and he is the end and the Reſt of all the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in whom all the Promiſes are <hi>Yea and Amen;</hi> and without him all is as nothing, and all that comes before him are Thieves and Robbers, and he it is that abideth a Prieſt for ever, and his Spirit of Truth is
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152237:47"/>
it which all People and Profeſſors whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhould firſt wait to receive, thereby to be led into that true ſpiritual Worſhip, which alone God accepteth; leſt they and their worſhip and building fall together, in a day when there is none to deliver.</p>
                  <p>And then thus I <hi>query;</hi> If Chriſts own dear Diſciples, who had forſook all and followed him, (not <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Baptiſts</hi>) did not come to receive this Spirit, by hearing all the words which he ſpoke unto them, but by waiting after the words were ended; Then, whether thoſe that have not forſaken all (nor ſo much as the Worlds faſhions) do now come to receive the Spirit by reading, hearing or profeſſing the ſame words of Chriſt, now written, or any other part of the Scriptures?</p>
                  <p>Or, whether a Proud man hath received this Spirit, or a Lyar, or Prophane Perſon, or any Wiſe or Prudent man whatſoever, by any means or way of his? And whether any ſuch ever did, have, or can or may by any induſtry, or other way or means at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to this Spirit which leadeth in the true worſhip of God, but as it is freely given forth from God? and then whether all people are not to be led by that Spirit
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152237:47"/>
(which God freely giveth) into the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; becauſe Chriſt ſaid, <hi>the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhould lead,</hi> which indeed doth lead in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth, and nothing elſe doth ſo? And they that have not received this from God to lead them, are not yet come to be led by that which the Sons and Children of God were, and are led by.</p>
                  <p>And the Miniſtration of the Spirit, which all are now to be taught by, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to be known, in the neareſt, ſecret inviſible manner, and is more out of the ſight, comprehenſion, and reach of mans wiſdom, then any other Miniſtration; and it is given forth from the clear Fountain it ſelf, unto the ſoul-ſatisfaction of man, when he is come to the end of words; or having heard much, or all the words that can be ſpoken of it, remaineth unſatisfied, in a reſtleſs longing deſire, to find, receive, feel and enjoy the thing it ſelf, which the words declare of; and that which ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the true thirſting-ſoul, comes clearly from God, to the refreſhing of the inward parts of man, and filling of the empty, barren, hungry ſpirit, which cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied without Gods in-dwellings; and thus the Diſciples were led along, and at
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152237:48"/>
laſt, in a fooliſh way to the great Profeſſors they waited among them in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Lord had regard unto them, and ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his own Spirit unto them, and then they were filled with the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>And the ſecret inviſible hand of God whoſe Power was and is felt in my heart, having out of the ſight of fleſh and blood, in the hidden counſel of his ſecret Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> led me by the vertue of the operation an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> drawings thereof, through thoſe thing which thereby I come to leave behinde and to receive and feel that which no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> goeth before, and is my Leader, in whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Covenant of Life Eternal, my ſoul is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſatisfied; and ſo by good experience o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lords leadings, and from an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental knowledge, ſenſible feeling, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> preſent enjoyment of the incomes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Spirit of Truth and Life, which filled the inward parts with the Holineſs of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſelf, and giveth power to do the thing required before of God, even from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> right and good underſtanding thereof, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this written; That where it meets with the like condition in a weary Traveller, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may anſwer its own, and be helpfull to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weak and feeble, that ſuch may not giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:152237:48"/>
over preſſing forwards, nor faint in their long travel, though many Mountains, on which they did nouriſh themſelves for a time will not yeeld them Bread now; yet that they may with me, and the reſt of the Followers and Friends of Chriſt (paſt and preſent) always continue following the Spirit as it leads, until the inward man be filled therewith, and ſo power and ſtrength from God come to be known, and received in every particular.</p>
                  <p>For thus it is with Chriſts Followers now they are not ſatisfied until they are filled with that which they have heard of, and their ſouls thirſted after; and ſo it was with them then, and they were filled with what they wanted before; and then, from that which they were filled with they ſpoke forth; and ſo they did teach the Nations, and brought People under the Power of God, and baptized them into that, and dipt them into the Name of the Father, and brought them under that which ſaveth from Sin, and plunged them into the holy Spirit; and as they teach'd they did this, baptizing as they did teach, and plunging them (as their doctrine went forth) into that which waſheth and purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152237:49"/>
the Conſcience from the filth and guilt of Sin, of which the outward Baptiſm wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a figure of this which ſaveth; and ſo their Doctrine was from an inward Life, and proceeded from that which was inviſible; and ſo reached to that which wanted life in the Hearers, and ſo brought up the Power of God over them, and them under it, and into it; for the Word is <hi>[Into]</hi> and they were to bring people <hi>into</hi> the Name, (not Water) and they were to bring or baptize them <hi>into</hi> the Name, <hi>as</hi> they did teach, Go ye and teach, <hi>baptizing into;</hi> Baptizing is in the <hi>Preſent Tenſe,</hi> when they did teach: and ſo here, the ſpiritual and inward Baptiſm goes along with the Preaching of the Word of Life, which is inward, and brings man into an inward enjoyment of God, being baptized <hi>into</hi> his Name, which is a Strong Tower, which preſerveth from the power of the Devil: and we all who are brought into this, and are come in here, are all by one Spirit bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into one Body, and ſo worſhip God in the Spirit, having the heart ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, by the waſhing of Regeneration in the Miniſtration of the Goſpel of Peace, whereby there is a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152237:49"/>
nigh to God, (being brought into his Name) and a free acceſs to the Throne of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat Grace, which ſaveth from and out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Humphrey Smith.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Diſcovery of Mans return to his firſt Eſtate, by the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Power of God in the great work of Regeneration.</head>
               <p>ALL Men and Women, behold, and ſee in what eſtate you were created.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And God ſaid, Let us make Man in our Image; God created Man in his own Image, and in the Image of God created he him, male and female created he them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Lord took Man, and put him in the Garden of Eden, to dreſs, and keep it. And the Lord God commanded the Man, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Of every Tree in the Garden thou mayſt freely eat, but of the Tree of Knowledge of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152237:50"/>
good and evil thou ſhalt not eat of it: for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dye the death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Serpent was more ſubtile than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> beaſt of the field which the Lord God b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> made; he ſaid unto the Woman, Ye ſhall n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſurely dye: for God doth know that in the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> you eat thereof, your eyes ſhall be opened, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ye ſhall be as God, knowing good and evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And when the Woman ſaw the Tree w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> good for food, and that it was pleaſant un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wiſe, ſhe took the fruit thereof, and did ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and gave alſo to her husband with her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he did eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked, and they ſewed fig-leaves together, and made th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Aprons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they heard the voice of the Lord God, walking in the Garden in the cool of the day, and</hi> Adam <hi>and his Wife hid themſelves from the preſence of the Lord among the Trees of the Garden: and the Lord God called unto</hi> Adam, <hi>and ſaid unto him, Where art thou?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he ſaid, I heard thy Voice in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and was afraid; and becauſe I was naked, I hid my ſelf: and he ſaid, Who told thee
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152237:50"/>
that thou waſt naked? haſt thou eaten of the Tree wherof I commanded thee that thou ſhouldeſt not eat? And the Man ſaid, The Woman whom thou gaveſt to be with me, ſhe gave me of the Tree, and I did eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Lord God ſaid unto the Woman, What is this that thou haſt done? The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaid, The Serpent beguiled me, and I did eat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Lord God ſaid unto the Serpent, Becauſe thou haſt done this, thou art curſed above all Cattel, and above every Beaſt of the field: upon thy belly ſhalt thou go, and duſt ſhalt thou eat all the dayes of thy life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I will put enmity betwixt thee and the Woman, and betwixt thy ſeed and her Seed; it ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Lord God ſaid, Behold this Man is become as one of us, to know good and evil: and now leſt he put forth his hand, &amp; take alſo of the Tree of Life, and eat, and live for ever. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord God ſent him forth from the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of</hi> Eden, <hi>to till the ground from whence he was taken, and he drove out the Man, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the Eaſt of the Garden of</hi> Eden <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims, and a flaming Sword, which turned every way, to keep the Way of the Tree of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:152237:51"/>Every Man and Woman, behold and ſee how you are fallen from the eſtate and condition you are created in; yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were created in the Image of God, to delight alone in him, but you are fallen in obeying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the counſel of the Serpent, and are driven out of the Preſence of God into the Earth, and there your minds are feeding upon the duſt of the Earth, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted objects which will periſh: ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in Father and Mother, ſome in Wife and Children, ſome in Houſe and Lands, ſome in Money and Gold, ſome in Meats and Drinks, ſome in Raiment what they ſhall put on, ſome in Luſts and Pleaſures; in Wantonneſs, in vain idle Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fooliſh Jeſting and Laughter, which is madneſs and folly; and ſome in Honour and Preferment in this World, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their hearts are lifted up in Pride and Exaltation above others whom they have Power over, not conſidering how you are driven out from the Preſence of the Lord, wherein you were placed in the beginning; and ſome there are that feed upon the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Scripture, which is death, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending God and Chriſt in their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from what the Saints of the moſt high
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152237:51"/>
God have ſpoken forth from the Life they enjoyed in Chriſt Jeſus, which was in them the hope of their glory; and man in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine wiſdom ſteals the Saints words into his underſtanding, and never knew the Life and Power thereof in himſelf, and ſo ſpeaks a divination of his own brain, a riddle to his own heart; and while he ſpeaks to others, himſelf i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a caſt-away.</p>
               <p>Every man and woman in particular, deal juſtly with your hearts, and ſee where your hearts are, and what they delight in, for in ſome of theſe created objects you delight in, and feed upon, if you cannot witneſs your change by the Eternal and Powerfull Word of Truth; for into the Earth you are driven from the preſence of God, and theſe are the fruits which ſpring out of the Earth which are in your hearts, Self-love, Pride, Covetouſneſs, Anger, Revenge, Haſtineſs, Frowardneſs, Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, Hard-heartedneſs, Cruelty and Oppreſſion, Luſt and Uncleanneſs, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, Impaciency and Unbelief, and you are fenced out, from coming to the Tree of Life, with Cherubims, and the flaming Sword, which turns every way to keep the Tree of Life. So every one ſee
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152237:52"/>
what you can witneſs of your return agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto God from whence you are ſeperated by the diſobedience and evil of your hearts, and ſee what is the ground of the hope o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your callings, and by what power you are acted in your obedience unto God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the power of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> or by the power of the ſecond: for if thou, upon the convincement of the evil of thy wayes, doſt not wait in the Light which is in thy conſcience, that convinceth thee of the evil of thy doings, for Power from the Lord to guide thee forth of the evil, which the Light diſcovers, which would guide thee into the Kingdom of God, but thou runneſt out into the wiſdom of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> to ſeek the Kingdom of God in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward forms and obſervations, according as thou comprehendeſt of the Saints practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thou imitateſt their practices in thy wiſdom, and though thou walk ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſtrictly in theſe outward forms, thou art alive in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſewing fig-leaves together to cover thy nakedneſs, a peice of new cloth in an old garment, thou art putting new wine into old bottles, and art building up a Tower to get up to God in thy Heatheniſh and Babyloniſh
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152237:52"/>
wiſdom, and confuſion will come upon thee; In the day when the Lord comes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook for fruit, thou wilt be found a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs Tree that cumbers the ground; <hi>Cain,</hi> with his offering up Sacrifice unto God in thy firſt nature; <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſeeking the bir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h-right with tears, who ſhall never find it, and all the fruit that is raiſed in thee is from <hi>Hagar</hi> the Bond-woman, and thou haſt thy end for thy ſelf in all that thou doſt, which is thy hire, which thou expecteſt in the end, life, for thy labour and obedience; and thou regardeſt not the glory of the Lord, and his fear is not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eyes: Therefore every man and woman, deal juſtly with your own hearts, under what name or title ſoever thou art, whether thou be a Teacher of others, or a Profeſſor of what thou comprehendeſt to be truth from the Teſtimony the Saints gave forth, from the Life and Power of Chriſt that was in them, and thou expecteſt Life in thy outward Forms and Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and mindeſt not to be guided by the Light, which is of Chriſt, in thy own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; which Light guided the Saints that gave forth the Scriptures: and while thou diſobeyeſt that Light, profeſs what
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152237:53"/>
thou wilt, thou art in the fall, <hi>firſt Adam</hi> is yet alive in thee; <hi>Cain</hi> is not yet baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor <hi>Eſau</hi> reprobated, nor the bond-woman and her ſon caſt out; which are all figures and types of the firſt nature, which is yet alive in thee, and thy will is thy guide, and thy heart is in the Earth, notwithſtanding all thy profeſſion, and thou art a painted beaſt, made drunk with the wine of the wrath of the Whore, which is thy wiſdom, which comprehends that which thou never didſt know manifeſt in it ſelf, and ſits deckt a well-favoured Harlot, above the Croſs of Chriſt; thou wilt be found a Thief and a Robber, who comes not in by the door, Jeſus Chriſt, but climes up ſome other way: and thus far went the Scribes and Phariſees, and the young man, who had kept the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from his youth, but when he ſhould have ſold all for Chriſt, he went away ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful: And thus far went <hi>Paul</hi> when he perſecuted Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Law he walked blameleſs; and all thy ſtrict walking to get life in obſervations according to the Letter, is ſtriving again to get to the Tree of Life by thy own power, who are fenced out with Cherubims,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152237:53"/>
and a flaming Sword, which turns every way to keep the Tree of Life; And if thou never ſaweſt thy ſelf fenced out from the preſence of God, notwithſtanding all thy righteouſneſs in obſervations, thou art not come ſo near God as to ſee the flaming Sword which is placed to meet thee in every way thou turneſt to get life in thy own power, and to cut thee down and kill thee, that Chriſt may be thy life, thou art alive in the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> and art in the death, for Death reigns over all from <hi>Adam to Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> is until the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> till <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> until <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and if thou canſt not witneſs that thou art come to <hi>Moſes,</hi> profeſs what thou wilt, thou haſt not ſet thy face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, nor one ſtep in the ſtrait and narrow way to Eternal Life, but art going the broad way to deſtruction, whatever thou be, whether a Teacher of others, or a Profeſſor of what thou comprehendeſt to be Truth from the Letter of the Scripture, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what form, name, or title ſoever thou be, thou art a dead man, and a dead wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the wrath of God abides on thee, though thou ſee it not; <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. there <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, ſaying, <hi>I was alive with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152237:54"/>
the Law once, but when the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came, ſin revived, and I dyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Friends, every one in particular, deal juſtly with your hearts, ſee what you can witneſs of your death with Chriſt by the powerfull Word of Truth, which enlightens the Conſcience, and condems ſin in the fleſh: for every one would aſcend with Chriſt to be partakers of the Life and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with him, but he becomes a ſtumbling-ſtone, to be baptized with him into his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and Death, to deſcend with him into Hell; and this thou muſt witneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever thou come to ſit with him in heavenly places; for it is they, and they alone that ſhall reign with him, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him; and they that are dead with him ſhall live with him: It is the dead that hear the Voice of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall live, Ariſe thou that ſleepeſt in the duſt of the Earth, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely in thy ſerpentine wiſdom, thy mind feeding upon the duſt of the Earth, created objects which will periſh; Ariſe, ſtand up to Judgment, that Chriſt may give thee Life. <hi>This is required of thee, O man, To do Juſtly, love Mercy, and to walk Humbly with thy God.</hi> Examine thy heart, and deal
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152237:54"/>
juſtly with thy own Soul: There is a Light in thy Conſcience, which Light is of Chriſt; minding, it will let thee ſee the Myſtery of Iniquity that lodgeth in thy heart, which is deceitfull and deſperately wicked; and this Light in thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which diſcovers unto thee the evil of thy heart, is of the eternal Word of God, and was from the beginning, according as it is written in the outward Teſtimony of the Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word is God, and the ſame was in the beginning with God; all things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made; in him was Life, and the Life was the Light of men. And the Light ſhineth in darkneſs, and the darkneſs comprehendeth it not.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ariſe out of your earthly wiſdom, and mind the Light in thy Conſcience, and wait on the Power of the Lord in it, and it will bring thee to judgment before the Throne of the Lamb, where the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law will be opened in thy heart, that will cry through thy earthly heart for Righteouſneſs and Judgment, and the Book will be opened in thee, where
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152237:55"/>
thou ſhalt ſee all written that thou haſt done in the body, and ſhalt give an account for every idle word, and receive thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for what thou haſt done, and thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is Wrath and Condemnation, which will paſs upon thee from the preſence of the Lamb, for thy diſobedience and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the righteous Law, which muſt be fulfilled; and what way ſoever thou turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to get life in outward forms and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, the flaming Sword, which is the righteous Law, that goes out of the mouth of the Lamb, 'twill turn every way, and meet thee, and cut thee down, and caſt thee into Hell, where there is weeping and wailing for want of the preſence of God, and thou canſt do nothing to pacify the Wrath of God which is gone out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. Now wouldſt thou hide thy ſelf as <hi>Adam</hi> did, when he appears in thy heart, thy fig-leav'd garment of prayers, tears, forms, outward obſervations accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy comprehenſion of the Letter, will not cover thy nakedneſs; it ſerved to cover thy nakedneſs from the ſight of men, but now when the Lord appears in thy heart, thou canſt not ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: Now comes <hi>Cain</hi> in thee to be
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152237:55"/>
driven from the face of God, to be a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive and a Vagabond in the Earth, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his Sacrifices; and <hi>Eſau</hi> in thee reprobated, never to have the bleſſing, though he ſeek it with tears; and the Bond-woman and her ſon caſt out, and the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> now ſlain with the ſharp Sword that goeth out of the mouth of the Lamb, and art made to give up thy ſoul to God, whoſe it is, to do with thee what he will; if he deſtroy thee for ever, he may; and if he ſave thee from eternal death, it is his free Love. Now art thou baptized with Chriſt into his Sufferings and Death, where thou lieſt ſealed down under the Eternal Judgment of God, and there periſheſt for ever, for any power or help thou haſt in thy ſelf; and this is the Adminiſtration of <hi>Moſes,</hi> where thou lieſt condemned for ever under the righteous Law, without any help or hope, until the Adminiſtration of the Prophets, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of a Chriſt that hath ſatisfied the righteous Law of God for thee, who art loſt and condemned under the power of the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> And now there is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret hope raiſed up in thy ſoul, and thou lookeſt up from under the condemning
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152237:56"/>
power of <hi>Moſes</hi> for a Saviour: And the Prophets are until <hi>John,</hi> and of all that were born of women there was not one greater then <hi>John,</hi> for he is a burning and ſhining Light that lets thee ſee the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of thy heart; and the Law ſhines in its purity to condemn the earthly man in thee, but he ſtrengthens the hope in thee that was raiſed up by the Prophets, to ſee the beauty and excellency of Jeſus Chriſt, which raviſheth thy loſt condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſoul, that thou art willing to ſell all for him, the Scripture now being fulfilled in thee who witneſſeth this from the dayes of <hi>John</hi> even until now; <hi>The Kingdom of God ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force:</hi> now is every Mountain and Hill laid low in thee, and crooked wayes made ſtraight, and the rough way in thee made ſmooth, and thou waiteſt in the Wilderneſs and loſt condition of thy ſelf, for the Salvation of God, to be manifeſt to thee in Jeſus Chriſt; and in the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time of the Father, the Son of man comes to thy ſoul as a thief in the night, as the Lightning from the Eaſt to the Weſt, ſo is his appearance in thee, and cauſeth thy dead ſoul to hear his voice, which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152237:56"/>
to it eternal Life freely through his own blood; and thy ſoul hears his voice, and by the word of his Power is made to live, and is ſealed up by the holy Spirit of Promiſe, the Spirit of God bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with thy ſpirit that thou art his child: Now comeſt thou to witneſs the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> to be a quickening Spirit, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> the promiſed Seed to be Heir for ever: And that <hi>the wages of Sin is death, but the Gift of God is Eternal Life:</hi> And <hi>that by Grace thou art ſaved, through Faith in the Lord Jeſus; not of works, leſt any ſhould boaſt:</hi> and he that hath Hope in him purifieth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as he is pure; and the love of Chriſt conſtrains thee now, who can witneſs this work of Regeneration manifeſt in thee, to follow him <hi>whitherſoever</hi> he goes; no more to obey him for Life as thou didſt, when thou waſt without, ſeeking him in Forms and Obſervations, but now the Love and Life thou enjoyeſt in Chriſt Jeſus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains thee to deny thy ſelf, and take up thy Croſs daily and follow him. Now art thou come into the beginning to live in the Lord, guided by the powerfull word of Faith, the Light that ſhines in thy heart. which is the Light of the City, <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:152237:57"/>
to whom thou art come to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Father in Spirit and Truth; and all that are come to walk in the Light of the City, <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> are the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, that are taught of God, to whom the New and Everlaſting Covenant is made according to the Promiſe of the Lord; <hi>This is the Covenant I will make with the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and with the Houſe of</hi> Judah, <hi>after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe dayes ſaith the Lord; I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts; and I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a People. And they ſhall teach no more every man his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, nor every man his Brother, ſaying, Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them to the greateſt of them. I will be merciful unto their unrighteouſneſs, and their Sins and their Iniquities will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member no more. And in this City there is no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it,</hi> which are borrowed lights, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpenſations, and teachings of men; <hi>for the glory of the Lord God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light thereof. And the Nations of them that are ſaved ſhall walk in the Light of it; and the Kings of the Earth bring their glory and honour unto it; and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152237:57"/>
there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or maketh a lie, but they</hi> ever <hi>which are written in the Lambs Book of Life: And the gates of it ſhall not be ſhut at all by day, for there ſhall be no night there, for the Lord God giveth them Light, and they ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Hallelujah to the Higheſt.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To all revolted Souls who have departed from the Councel of the Lord, and are made drunk with the wine of the wrath of the Fornication of the Whore, bewitched with the Mother of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, to return into ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where our Lord is Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</head>
               <p>WHoever thou art in whom the righteous Law of God, Jeſus Chriſt, the Light, in thee hath cryed through thy earthly heart for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Judgment, and there thou didſt ſtand arraigned before the Throne of the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152237:58"/>
Lamb, where the Book was opened in thee, and written therein all the deeds thou haſt done in the body, and the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Wrath and Judgement paſſed out of the mouth of the Lamb on thee for every idle word, and all that thou haſt done; and in this thy condemned eſtate, thou rann'ſt to and fro to hide thee from the Wrath of the Lamb, in reforming thy wayes, and ſtrictly obſerving what thou waſt convinced of to be the Will of God; but what way ſoever thou turnedſt in thy obedience towards God, to get life, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the flaming Sword turned that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded out of the mouth of the Lamb, and cut thee down, and caſt thee into Hell, where thou layeſt weeping and wailing under the Wrath of God ſealed down under his eternal Judgment for evermore, for any help or power thou hadſt in thy ſelf, until Jeſus Chriſt manifeſted eternal Love and Mercy freely to thy poor loſt condemned ſoul, and raiſed thee up to a lively hope, and ſealed thee up in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Life with his own blood. Now after the Witneſſes have ſealed up their Teſtimony, the Beaſt which is thy will, that aſcends out of the bottomleſs Pit of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152237:58"/>
thy deceived heart, which is deceitfull and deſperately wicked, hath made war againſt the Witneſſes, Chriſt in thee, and ſlain them, and they lie dead in the ſpiritual City of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where our Lord is crucified; and thou art made drunk with the Wine of the Wrath of the Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Whore, and bewitched with her Witchcrafts, who now tells thee, Whom he loves he loves to the end, and To the pure all things are pure; thou art no more under the Law but under Grace, and all things are alike; that when thou diſobeyeſt the pure Law, which once had power over thee, and it witneſſeth againſt thee ſecretly, crying in thy heart, Uſe thy liberty, but not as an occaſion to the fleſh, thou regardeſt not the Counſel of the Lord, but hearkens to the Mother of Harlots in thee, and cauſeth thee to wreſt the Scriptures to thine own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tells thee, the Law hath no power over thee, thou art under Grace, it is but the Law in thy members, that wars againſt the Law in thy mind, the acting of the humanity which acts in its place, that the Grace of God may appear more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly; God ſees no ſin in thee, for it is
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152237:59"/>
no more thou, but ſin that dwells in thee, and the former miſery thou waſt in under the Wrath of God, for the diſobeying of the Righteous Law, thou now treadeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy feet, and lies ſlain in ſpiritual <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> in thy heart, yet not put in grave, but lies in thy ſight, and lets thee ſee the evil of thy doings, and vexes and torments thy earthly and carnal heart in the midſt of all thy joy; but the Whore in thee, tells thee, that the former trouble thou waſt in, it was through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God, but now thou art grown up to a higher ſtature in Chriſt, to ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Love in whatſoever thou doſt, and now thou knowſt nothing but to eat, and to drink, and be merry, <hi>for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Bride-Chamber cannot mourn while the Bridegroom is with them;</hi> time was thou didſt mourn, but it was when the Bridegroom was not with thee; but now the Winter is paſt, and Summer come, and ſinging of Birds is heard in thy Land; and now waſh thy face, and anoint thy head with Oyl, that thou appear no more before men, as thou didſt when thou waſt a Phariſee: Now to be a friend to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Sinners, and become all to all,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152237:59"/>
that thou mayeſt win ſome, and whatever thou doſt, it is God that acts thee, for thou art not ſtronger then he to reſiſt him; and if he would have it otherwayes, how couldſt thou hinder it? ſo it is as it muſt be, and it cannot be otherwiſe. Thus the ſubtil Serpent windes into the mind of man, and cauſes him to wreſt the Scriptures to his own deſtruction, to draw back into Perdition.</p>
               <p>Wo, wo unto thee thou backſlider in heart, who chargeſt God, who is Purity it ſelf, to be the author of Sin, and the actor of thee in all thy filthy and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous walking, and haſt turned the Grace of God into wantonneſs, and takeſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſin, becauſe Grace abounds, and makeſt the coming of Chriſt (who came to fulfil the Law) to deſtroy it, through the evil of thy heart, that when the righteous Law cryes in thee for purity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns thee for thy unrighteous walking, then thou flieſt to the Free Grace in Chriſt, to ſave thee from the power of the Law; but thou ſhalt find the Law hath power over the fleſhly man as long as he lives, and the fleſhly man that now guides thee, is under the Law, until it be deſtroyed
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152237:60"/>
through Faith in Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>For he came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfil it,</hi> and the Saints witneſs it, though thou wreſt the words of <hi>Paul</hi> (when he declared his condition before he came to the fulneſs of ſtature in Chriſt) to thy own deſtruction. <hi>I ſee a Law in my members warring againſt the Law of my mind, bringing me into captivity to the Law of ſin which is in my members;</hi> but he gave not up himſelf to be a ſervant of ſin, as thou doſt, it was his burthen that made him to cry, <hi>Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death?</hi> and he waited in the Faith until he was freed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 2. <hi>For the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the Law of Sin and Death, that the righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in us who walk not after the Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh, but after the Spirit:</hi> He witneſſed Chriſt came in him to fulfil the Law, and ſo do all the Saints now, according to their growth; ſome witneſs the Law fulfilled <hi>in them,</hi> and others are waiting in the Faith patiently, following the Lord daily through the Croſs, until the Law be fulfilled. But thou art departed from the Counſel of the Lord thy God, and cauſeſt his Name to be evil
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152237:60"/>
ſpoken of, and haſt made the hearts of his People ſad, as they did that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of; <hi>For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt: whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is their ſhame, who mind earthly things.</hi> Theſe Scriptures are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in thee, which the Apoſtle menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>And while they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for of whom a man is overcome, of the ſame is he brought into bondage: For if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have eſcaped the pollutions of the World, through the knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, they are again entangled therein and overcome; the latter end of them is worſe with them than the beginning. For it had been better for them not to have known the way of Righteouſneſs, than after they have known it, to turn from the Holy Commandment delivered unto them. But it happened unto them according to the true Proverb, The Dog is turned to his own vomit again, and the Sow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire.</hi> And thou mayſt read what will be manifeſt to thee from the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:152237:61"/>For if we ſin wilfully, after we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the knowledge of the Truth, there remains no more Sacrifice for ſin, but a fearfull looking for of Judgment, and fiery Indignation, which ſhall devour the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</p>
               <p>He that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> Law dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy, how much ſorer puniſhment ſuppoſeſt thou, ſhalt thou be thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of, who haſt trodden under foot the Son of God, and haſt counted the Blood of the Covenant, wherewith thou waſt ſanctified, an unholy thing, and haſt done deſpight to the Spirit of Grace? and we know him that hath ſaid, <hi>Vengeance belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto Me, I will recompence, ſaith the Lord:</hi> It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the Living God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen, Repent, and do thy firſt work,</hi> in minding that Light of Jeſus Chriſt, in thee, before whom thou once ſtoodeſt condemned for that thou now liveſt in: Prize the time, and give up to be guided by the Counſel of the Lord in thee, the Light of thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that diſcovers every vain thought; wait on the power that is preſent with the Light, and it will daſh <hi>Babylons</hi> children
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152237:61"/>
againſt the ſtones, which is ſin in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, ſo will thy carnal mind be brought to the Croſs daily, and thy heart will be purged with the Spirit of Judgment, and the Spirit of Burning: Kiſs the Son in obeying his Counſel, the Light in thee, <hi>leſt thou periſh in the way; for if his Anger be kindled a little, bleſſed are they that truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Diſcovery of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">To all enſlaved Captives in <hi>Babylon's</hi> Kingdom, who are made drunk with the wine of the Wrath of her Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and bewitched through the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of her Inchantments.</head>
               <p>FRiends, <hi>Babylon</hi> is within you, the <hi>Mother of Harlots</hi> is within you, and ſhe bewitcheth you through the abundance of her Sorceries; and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is within you that ariſeth out of the bottomleſs Pit of the deceived heart, which is deceitfull
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152237:62"/>
and deſperately wicked; and the Beaſt which all the world wanders after, is your wills, that makes war againſt the Lamb of God in you, which is the Light that makes manifeſt the evil of your hearts; and your wiſdom is the great Whore that ſits upon the Beaſt, that ariſeth out of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit of the deceitfull heart, and ſhe finds out many deceitfull inventions to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the beaſtly <hi>will</hi> alive, having a golden Cup in her hand, full of the Abominations of the Earth, and this Golden Cup is your outward profeſſions, glorious compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions and conceivements of God and Chriſt, imtiating what the Saints did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power, according as they were moved by the operation of the Spirit of the Moſt High God, and you imitate the Saints pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice by your wiſdom.</p>
               <p>There is nothing but confuſion in the Kingdom of <hi>Babylon;</hi> So come you to be divided into ſo many particular Forms, as <hi>Presbyterians, Independants, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and divers others, that are in outward worſhips, painted over with glorious words; and yet you whoſe wills guide you, are paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Beaſts, bewitched with the Mother of Harlots, notwithſtanding all your outward
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152237:62"/>
profeſſions and glorious obſervations, they are but the golden Cup, and within you are full of the Abominations of the Earth, as <hi>Self-Love, Covetouſneſs, Luſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Frowardneſs, Backbiting, Slandering, Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſs, Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion, grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faces of the Poor, Impatiency</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief,</hi> and <hi>the fear of the Lord is not before your eyes;</hi> and thus you lie enſlaved Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in the Kingdom of <hi>Babylon,</hi> refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your hearts in the Creature— enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which will periſh; ſome in Father and Mother, ſome in Wife and Children, ſome in Houſe and Land, ſome in Gold and Silver; ſome in Self wiſdom, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in themſelves; ſome in Honour and Preferment in this World: and when there is enjoyment of theſe viſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then there is content; and when they are taken away, there is trouble, the mind alwayes plodding, contriving, and acting every way to get of the creatures what the heart luſteth after, and he that gets the moſt is higheſt exalted; ſo every one is exalted above another, and there is nothing but Tyranny, Cruelty and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion among you, you ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Babylon; And in her was found the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152237:63"/>
blood of the Prophets, and of the Sains, and all that were ſlain upon the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Merchants of <hi>Babylon</hi> are your Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; who draw you from your Guide, which is the pure Light of Chriſt in you, to ſeek the Kingdom of God in obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions without you, contrary to the mind of Chriſt: <hi>The Kingdom of God comes not with obſervations, neither ſhall they ſay, Lo here, or, Lo there; for, behold, the Kingdom of God is within you.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe your Merchants have no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for their Merchandize, which they ſell to you enſlaved Captives for ſo many hundreds in the year, and is paid in the Nation, or elſewhere: for theſe obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they tell you you muſt obſerve, or elſe you cannot come to the Kingdom of Heaven, though they are contrary to the Scripture, as are practiſed by them; there is no Scripture that witneſſeth their call to the Miniſtry by humane wiſdom; <hi>Not many great, not many noble, not many wiſe after the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no Scripture which teſtifies of any that Jeſus Chriſt ſent forth that made a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with the People for ſo much a year, as theſe do that profeſs themſelves to be ſent of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:152237:63"/>This is the call of the Miniſters of Chriſt, <hi>Paul an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, neither of man, nor by man, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſend you forth</hi> (ſaith Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>as Lambs among Wolves: Into what Town or City ye enter, enquire who is worthy; and if they receive you, there abide, eating ſuch things as is ſet before you: the Labourer is worthy of his meat: freely ye have received, freely miniſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe whom Jeſus Chriſt commits the Word of Eternal life unto, and calls them forth to declare it unto others, the Love of Jeſus Chriſt, which is ſealed up to their ſouls through his own blood, conſtrains them to give up themſelves to death, in witneſſing forth the Eternal Life they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy in Chriſt; as it was, it is, <hi>The Love of Chriſt conſtraineth me to preach the Goſpel,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul:</hi> But theſe your Merchants are they which have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray, following the way of <hi>Balaam</hi> the ſon of <hi>Boſor,</hi> who loved the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of unrighteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>And as there is no Scripture for their call to the Miniſtry by their human learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor making bargains with the people
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152237:64"/>
for ſo much in the year: ſo there is no Scripture for theſe obſervations they call the Ordinances of God, as they are practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them.</p>
               <p>There is no Scripture, that Chriſt, or any that he ſent forth, did take a Child, and ſprinkle water on its face, and ſaid, in ſo doing, <hi>they baptized it into the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suffer little Children to come unto me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God; for whoſoever ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Kingdom of God as a little Child, ſhall not enter therein;</hi> He ſets the Child as a type and a figure to ſhew forth to every one, that they muſt become as a little Child, depending upon the Will of God, before they enter into the Kingdom of God: He took them up in his arms, and put his hands on them, and bleſſed them, but that he ſprinkled water on their faces, and ſaid, <hi>He baptized them into his Church,</hi> there is no ſuch Scripture.</p>
               <p>Another obſervation your Teachers tell you you muſt obſerve, is, hearing theſe Studied Sermons, in taking a part of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and adding to it their wiſdom, calls it <hi>The Word of God,</hi> which is contrary to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152237:64"/>
the Scripture; but they ſay, <hi>They have Chriſt for an example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There was delivered to him the Book of the Prophet Iſaiah, and when he had open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Book, he found where it was written, The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel unto the poor, he hath ſent me to heal the broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, to preach deliverance to the Captives: and recovering of the ſight of the blind, and to ſet at liberty them that are bruiſed, to preach the acceptable year of the Lord: And he cloſed the Book, and ſate down: and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſay unto them, This day is the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fulfilled in your ears: And all bare him witneſs, and wondred at the gracious words that proceeded out of his mouth;</hi> He was the ſubſtance of the Propheſie, which was then fulfilled in him.</p>
               <p>This is no ground for any to take the Saints words, and to add to it their wiſdom, and call that <hi>the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prophet that hath a Dream, let him tell a Dream: He that hath my Word let him ſpeak my Word faithfully. What is the Chaff to the Wheat, ſaith the Lord? <hi>Is not my word like a fire, and like a hammer,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>that breaks the Rocks in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152237:65"/>
pieces?</hi> All to whom the Word of the Lord is committed, can witneſs it to be as a fire within them, and as a hammer that break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the rocks in pieces, ſubjecting all in the heart under the power of it ſelf; ſo it alone rules and guides him, that he is what he ſpeaks; that if he had never ſeen any thing that the Saints have declared without him, he had known what is manifeſt in him; and he to whom the Word is thus made manifeſt, is a true Miniſter of Chriſt, who is called to ſpeak the Word faithfully.</p>
               <p>But theſe that call themſelves, <hi>your Teachers,</hi> and make bargains with you, for ſo much by the year, they never witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the word of the Lord, <hi>in them,</hi> as a fire, and like a hammer that breaketh the Rocks in pieces; ſo they never had any thing to have ſpoken of the Lord, but as they have ſtoln it from the teſtimony of the Saints; So they ſpeak a divination of their own brain; a riddle to their own hearts, and whilſt they ſpeak to others, themſelves are caſt-aways.</p>
               <p>And the Lord teſtifies againſt them, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am againſt the Prophets, ſaith the Lord, that ſteal my Word every one from his Neighbour.</hi>
               </p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:152237:65"/>
                  <hi>Behold, I am againſt the Prophets, ſaith the Lord, that uſe their tongue, and ſay, He ſaith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold, I am againſt them that propheſie falſe Dreams, ſaith the Lord, and to tell them, and cauſe my People to err by their Lyes, and by their lightneſs, yet I ſent them not, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them; therefore they ſhall not profit the People at all, ſaith the Lord:</hi> And this fruit is made manifeſt of the Miniſtry that hath been in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Obſervation your Teachers bid you obſerve, which is contrary to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as it is practiſed by them in ſinging of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms in Meeter, taking <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s words, who was a man after Gods own heart, and putting words into the mouthes of poor ignorant People to ſing that which they never knew, and ſo cauſeth them to blaſpheme the Name of God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Let us ſing to the Praiſe and Glory of God,</hi> As,
<q>
                     <l>O Lord I am not puft in mind,</l>
                     <l>I have no ſcornfull eye,</l>
                     <l>I do not exerciſe my ſelf</l>
                     <l>in things that be to high:</l>
                  </q>
When they never knew any change wrought in their minds, and ſo cauſeth
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152237:66"/>
the People to lye. And cauſing them to ſing <hi>David</hi>'s Prayers, as, <hi>O Lord rebuke me not in thy Wrath, neither chaſten me in thy hot diſpleaſure, for thine arrows ſtick faſt in me, and thy hand preſſeth me ſore: for my iniquities are gone over my head as an heavy burthen, they are too heavy for me to bear; my wounds ſtink, and are corrupt, becauſe of my fooliſhneſs; I am troubled, I am bowed down greatly, I go mourning all the day long:</hi> And may be none of you in all that place can witneſs the condition, and ſo blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemes the Name of God, who will be worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth: and this is the rule given out from him, <hi>If any be afflicted, let him pray; if any be merry, let him ſing Pſalms:</hi> And there is none merry but the Ranſomed of the Lord, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to <hi>Sion</hi> with joy and ſinging, <hi>and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their heads, they ſhall obtain joy and gladneſs, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All people may ſearch the Scriptures, and ſee how you have been deceived by your Teachers, who have cauſed you to ſeek your loſt God in carnal and dead ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, which they have not any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for: all ceaſe from them; for the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152237:66"/>
Lord complains of them, <hi>The Leaders of my People cauſe them to err, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> and now are theſe Scriptures ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in theſe men, which the Apoſtle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of.</p>
               <p>This know alſo, <hi>That in the laſt dayes pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous times ſhall come; for men ſhall be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of their own ſelves, covetous, proud, boaſters, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, unthankfull, unholy.</hi> All people ſee, are not your Teachers ſo, ſelf-lovers? before they come at you, they muſt know what they muſt have: covetous, griping for much; and if you will not give them ſo much as they can have in another place, they will not come at you: here is ſelf-love and covetouſneſs manifeſted; —<hi>without natural affection, Truce-breakers, falſe-Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, Traytors, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God, having a Form of Godlineſs, but denying the Power thereof; from ſuch</hi> the Apoſtle exhorts to <hi>turn away.</hi> All People behold and ſee, all theſe Scriptures are fulfilled in your Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: they ſpeak againſt Pride, and live in it; againſt covetouſneſs, and live in it: they teach by words to be naturally-affectionated one towards another, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152237:67"/>
they walk contrary, cauſing poor people to pay to maintain them in pride and high ranks in the Earth, who can ſcarce get bread for their bellies, and clothes for their backs; yet they force them to pay to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being void of all natural affections: and they are Truce-breakers, breaking all Bonds and Covenants, if they can get more money in another place. Thus they ſhew forth to all the world, that they are <hi>lovers of Pleaſures more then lovers of God,</hi> and <hi>have a form of Godlineſs</hi> in words, <hi>but deny the power thereof; from ſuch turn away:</hi> for, <hi>of this ſort are they which creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women, laden with ſin, and divers luſts.</hi> Theſe Scriptures are fulfilled in your Teachers, every one hath his particular houſe to creep into, where none muſt come but themſelves, or whom they pleaſe, which is contrary to the practiſe of Chriſt, or any that he ſent forth: they went through the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Towns, Cities, Villages, according as they were guided by the Spirit of God, to declare what he gave them to ſpeak: and your Teachers lead ſilly women cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, laden with ſin, and led away with divers luſts, ever learning, and never able
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152237:67"/>
to come to the knowledge of the Truth: Do not they tell you to look for Chriſt's coming in ſuch Obſervations as they ſet up? which is nothing but the inventions of their brains; for Chriſt tells you, <hi>The Kingdom of God comes not with obſervations,</hi> but is <hi>within you.</hi> But many of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that the Light in your Conſcience, which makes manifeſt the evil of your hearts, is the Kingdom of God, calling it the light of a corrupt conſcience; ſo ſhut the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven againſt men, and will neither enter in themſelves to be guided by the <hi>pure Light</hi> of the Kingdom of Chriſt <hi>within them,</hi> nor ſuffer them that are entring in, to enter, as the Scribes and Phariſees did: <hi>Now as</hi> Jannes and Jambres <hi>withſtood</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſo do theſe men reſiſt the Truth; men of corrupt minds, Reprobates concerning the Faith: but they ſhall proceed no further, for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt to all men, as theirs alſo was: and no man ſhall buy their Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize any more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All you enſlaved Captives in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Babylon,</hi> why will you lay out your Money for that which is not Bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfies not? hearken diligently unto Jeſus Chriſt, the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152237:68"/>
Light that lets you ſee the evil of your hearts, to be guided by it, and you ſhall eat that which is good. <hi>Encline your ears,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and come unto me; hear, and your ſouls ſhall live, and I will make an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant with you, even the ſure Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of David:</hi> Mind the call of a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and tender Father in the Lord Jeſus, who calls, <hi>Come forth of Babylon my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and touch no unclean thing, and I will receive you, and will be a Fath r unto you, and ye ſhall be my Sons and Daughters, ſaith the Lord God Almighty.</hi> Friends, prize your times, ſlight not the day of the Lords Mercy, for he waits to be gracious, and ſaith, <hi>I ſtretch forth my arm all the day long to a backsliding, and gainſaying People.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, mind your conditions, deal juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your own hearts, ſee what your hearts have fellowſhip with, and guide your minds, for the Kingdom of Chriſt is <hi>within you,</hi> it is not in obſervations, as your Teachers tell you, for they deceive you; therefore Chriſt forewarned us for looking forth at thoſe which would come in the latter dayes, that would ſay, <hi>Lo here is Chriſt, lo there is Chriſt!</hi> as it is in theſe our dayes; ſome ſay, <hi>Lo here is Chriſt
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152237:68"/>
in the Presbyterian practiſe;</hi> the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants</hi> ſay, <hi>He is there,</hi> and the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſay, <hi>Lo he is here:</hi> But Friends, mind what Chriſt ſaith unto you, <hi>believe them not,</hi> look not forth, the Kingdom of Chriſt is not in any of thoſe, nor in any other outward obſervations, but (be warned) the Kingdom of Chriſt is <hi>in you,</hi> and that is the Light that lets you ſee the evil of your hearts: and Chriſt compares it to a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, the leaſt of all Seeds, and it grows up above all other herbs, and becomes a Tree that the Fowls of the Air lodge therein: and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares it to a little Leaven, that a woman took and hid in three meaſures of Meal, and it leavened the whole Lump. Theſe are earthly parables and figures, which Chriſt layes down, ſpeaking to the earthly and carnal heart of man, that he might read his condition within. Therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not the day of ſmall things, but mind the Counſel of the Lord Jeſus, the little Light, that ſhines in thy dark heart; look upon the figures, the parables. The little Leaven which is hid in three meaſures of meal, it changeth the whole lump into the nature of it ſelf: So the little Light that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152237:69"/>
ſhine, in thy dark heart, is the powerfull Word of Faith, <hi>which was in the beginning, by which all things were created, and without him was nothing made; this Word is Life, and the Life is the Light of men, and Light ſhines in Darkneſs, and the Darkneſs comprehends it not:</hi> This Light is the Word of Faith the Apoſtle exhorted to take heed unto; <hi>Say not in thy heart, Who ſhall aſcend up to Heaven to fetch Chriſt down? or down into the deep to fetch him up? the Word is nigh thee, in thy heart and n thy mouth, and this is the Word of Faith which we preach, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of the holy One, given of the Father, whereby we need not to teach one another, but as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing teacheth us, which is Truth and no lye, which is the ſure word of Propheſie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye do well to take heed, as unto a Light ſhining in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the Day-Star ariſe in your hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All People return within, give up your ſelves freely to be guided by that Light, that diſcovers to you the evil of your hearts, and none be diſcouraged, becauſe you ſee an evil heart, but prize the Love of God that diſcovers it to you, and whatever the Light makes manifeſt to you to be evil: Wait on the Lord for Power, and he will
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:152237:69"/>
give thee power to obey, and in being faithfull in a little, more will be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated from the Lord, ſo will the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law be ſet up in your hearts, that will cry through your earthly and carnal hearts for Righteouſneſs and Judgment, and ſo will bring you to an account for every idle word, and all deeds done in the body. Look up unto the Lord againſt whom you have ſinned, and he will arm you with power to what he layes upon you, with patience to undergo his Will, until all the Powers of the Earth in you be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed and ſlain under his righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; then will Judgment be brought forth into Victory, that you can no longer live without the loving kindneſs of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Now is the Parable fulfilled, the little grain of Muſtard-Seed grown up above all herbs; and the little Leaven hath leavened the whole Lump; and the Prodigal ſtarved for ever, if his Father receive him not free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into his houſe.</p>
               <p>Thou that canſt witneſs this condition, ſtand ſtill in the Will of God, he will raiſe up his Seed in thee to truſt in his Name, and to delight in the Eternal Covenant of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152237:70"/>
Love and Life, he hath made with thy ſoul in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and will guide thee by the Word of his Power, in a way thou knoweſt not, forth of <hi>Babylon</hi> (where thou waſt an enſlaved Captive, under the power of the filthy Beaſt, which is thy will, and the Whore the Mother of Witchcrafts, which is thy wiſdom, which enthralled thee under the powers of Darkneſs, to ſatisfie the Luſt of thine own heart which led thee to deſtruction) up to <hi>Sion,</hi> to live by Faith in the Lord Jeſus, which will purifie thy heart, and ſet thy ſoul free from under the powers of Darkneſs, into the glorious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Sons of God, where thou ſhalt ſing the Songs of <hi>Sion, Hallelujahs</hi> and <hi>Praiſes</hi> for evermore, unto the Lord God that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:152237:70"/>
               <head>To all enſlaved, hard-hearted, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Jews in this Nation and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, who are made drunk with the wiſdom of the Whore, and bewitched through the abundance of her Sorceries, to put the Day of the Lord afar off; looking for Chriſts coming in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as the hard-hearted unbelieving Jews in the Letter, did for his coming in the Fleſh, according to the Promiſe; but they limitted the Holy-One, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their carnal wiſdom, expected his coming in great pomp and glory: and when he came in that poor deſpiſed way, contrary to their expectations, they ſtumbled at him, and would not own him to be their Saviour, but roſe up againſt him, and put him to death, <hi>Mat. 27.1,</hi> to <hi>verſ. 50.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEhold, you hard hearted and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Jews,</hi> do you not look for Chriſt coming in the Spirit according to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152237:71"/>
his Promiſe, as they did for his coming in the fleſh? but you limit the Holy One, as they did, expecting Chriſt to come in power and glory, according to your own fancies; and ſo put the day of the Lord afar off you, in rejecting and deſpiſing the Counſel of Jeſus Chriſt the pure Light in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, which lets you ſee every evil thought, word and action, and cries behind you, <hi>This is the Way, walk in it:</hi> but you diſobey the Light, and hearken to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of your hearts, as the Jews in the Letter did, who put Chriſt to death; and ſo you ſlay the Witneſſes in Spiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> in your hearts, where our Lord is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, in not regarding the Counſel of Chriſt, which is that Light that ſhines in your dark hearts, which knocks at the door, according to his Word; <hi>I ſtand at the door and knock: if any man hear my Voice, and open the door I will come in to him, and will ſup with him, and he with me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh thou enſlaved Soul under the power of <hi>Babylon</hi> in thee, Come forth, mind the Light in thee, which is the ſure Word of Prophecy, whereunto you do well to take heed, as unto a Light ſhining in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day-ſtar
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152237:71"/>
ariſe in your hearts: ſtand not out againſt this ſecret Counſel of Chriſt in you, leſt you periſh in your gain ſayings; for, if his Anger be kindled a little, bleſſed are all they that truſt in him. All give up, give up freely to be guided by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Lord, the Light in you, believing in his Power that is preſent with the Light; he will lead you daily through the Croſs, in the ſtreight way of his Sufferings and death, where the old man will be put off with his deeds, and ſo you ſhall have right to the Tree of Life, and ſhall enter with him through the Gates into the City, <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> where you ſhall have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Father and the Son, and an Inheritance with thoſe that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, and ſhall reign as Kings upon the Earth, to the praiſe and glory of the riches of the Grace of our heavenly Father, to whom alone be all Power, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, Honour and Glory, for ever and ever:</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:152237:72"/>
               <head>A Word from the Lord to all that are waiting on the Lord in <hi>Sion:</hi> and to thoſe that are weeping, and are ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord their God, asking the way to <hi>Sion</hi> with their faces thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</head>
               <p>FEar not, ye Mourners in <hi>Sion,</hi> the Lord waits on you to be gracious unto you; and though he give you the Bread of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity now, and the Water of Affliction, yet ſhall not your Teachers be removed into Corners any more, but your eyes ſhall ſee your Teachers, and your ears ſhall hear a voice behind you, ſaying, <hi>This is the Way, walk in it,</hi> when you turn to the right hand, or the left: Therefore every one of you mind the Light, which is of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>in you,</hi> that judgeth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs of your hearts; give up to be guided by the pure Light <hi>in you,</hi> which is your Teacher, the Counſel of Jeſus Chriſt, and it will bring Judgement forth unto Victory, and whatever he makes mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to you to be his Will: <hi>Wait on the Lord
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152237:72"/>
in his Counſel, and he will give you power to obey, and when you have obeyed his Will, take heed of departing from the Counſel of the Lord,</hi> which is the <hi>Light within you,</hi> to hearken to the counſel of your own hearts, which will draw your minds to look back at your obedience, and the experiences you have paſſed through; ſo will the Beaſt which received a deadly wound with the Sword, the Righteous Law, that goeth out of the mouth of the Lamb, in you, his deadly wound will be healed, (and ſits a painted Beaſt above the Croſs of Chriſt, working lying wonders in your hearts, and imitating the operation of the Power of God, who is purifying his Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with the Spirit of Judgment, and the Spirit of Burning) and the Beaſt in you, that taſted of the Power of God, when he received his deadly wound under the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, now can imitate the ſame in deceit, and cauſe fire to come down from Heaven in the ſight of men, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating the operation of the Spirit of Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo deceives himſelf and all that dwell upon the Earth, he is made manifeſt to all that dwell in the heavenly Light in their hearts. All Friends, mind your
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152237:73"/>
                  <hi>Watch,</hi> for the Adverſary, the Devil, goes about like a roaring <hi>Lion,</hi> ſeeking whom he may devour; abide in the Counſel of the Lord, which is the Light in you, and you will diſcern between the Beaſt, which is Antichriſt in his lying Wonders, and the Lamb Jeſus Chriſt, in the opperation of his Power; ſo you will come to try the ſpirits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether they be of God, yea or no; all that are guided by the Beaſt have their life in ſpeaking and acting in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward opperations what they once expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced, and what they comprehended to be truth, ſpeaking that they enjoy not, and is exalted in pride, the heart returned into the Earth. But thou that art guided by the Lamb, the Light in thy Conſcience, the righteous Law cries through thy earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heart, and brings it to Judgment, and thou canſt find no life in the opperation of the Power of God, nor in thy obedience, but whilſt the Preſence of the Lord is with thee in it; and when thou haſt done the Will of God in obeying what he hath made known unto thee, thou ſeeſt thy ſelf to be an unprofitable Servant, and haſt need of Patience, that thou mayeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Promiſe where thy Life is hid
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152237:73"/>
with Chriſt in God, to ſave thee freely for his Name ſake, or elſe thou periſheſt, and to carry thee on by his Mighty Power, or elſe thou falleſt, ſo thou haſt nothing to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in, but in the Lord.</p>
               <p>And as they that are guided by the Beaſt (which is <hi>Antichriſt</hi>) ſpeaks of the Truth, a riddle to their own hearts, not knowing the Power and Life of what they ſpeak, adding to the Word of the Lord, and the plagues and curſe of God will be added un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. But thou art guided by the Lamb Jeſus Chriſt, thou knoweſt when the Word of the Lord is committed to thee: <hi>If any have my Word,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>let him ſpeak my Word faithfully: Is not my Word like a fire,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and like a hammer, that breaketh the rocks in pieces?</hi> Thou canſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Word of the Lord to be as a fire, and as a hammer, to break the Rocks in pieces in thee, and bring down all in thee in ſubjection to it ſelf, and it alones rules in thee: and thou that canſt witneſs the Word of the Lord thus manifeſt in thee, thou art a true Meſſenger of the Lord; let not the deceit ſtop thy mouth, for the Word of the Lord that calls thee to ſpeak, ſhall perfect his Work for which he is ſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:152237:74"/>All Friends ſtand faſt in the Counſel and Will of God, be faithfull in following the Lamb daily through the Croſs, and none be diſcouraged: in temptations be content, look up to the Lord to keep you in the hour of temptations, for it is no ſin to be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but to yeeld to the Tempter: and when the Lord delivers you from the power of the Tempter, watch that your will get not from under the Croſs, but ſink down into the Love of God; and every one be content in what the Lord hath made manifeſt to you, and be faithfull according to your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, and more will be communicated to you, and none look forth at others condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for if you do, the Enemy will cauſe you to ſtumble, and you will come to a loſs in your own condition: wait patiently in the Counſel of the Lord, the Light in you, for he is making a ſhort work in the Earth, that you that come into the Vineyard at the eleventh hour, ſhall receive as much as they that came in at the third hour, and have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in the heat of the day.</p>
               <p>All ye children of the Lord lift up your heads, behold your King riding in Majeſty and Power upon the wild Aſs Colt, which is your wild nature, ſubjecting it to himſelf,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152237:74"/>
that you may enter with him through the Gates of the City into the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> where there enters nothing that worketh, abomination, and maketh a lie, but what is written in the Lambs Book of Life, and there you ſhall dwell in the Banqueting-houſe of the Lord for ever, ſeeding upon the feaſt of fat things, rejoycing in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Love and Mercy of your Souls, in the free Covenant of Life, in the Blood of Chriſt, who is the Lord of lords, and King of kings, God bleſſed forever; who is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on in majeſty and in power, conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and to conquer all the powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the hearts of his Saints, that they may reign as people upon the Earth, to the praiſe and glory of our God, who is taking unto him his Great Power, to reign in his Saints for evermore: To whom alone be all honour, glory, power, and eternal praiſes for ever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:152237:75"/>
               <head>A Word of Conſolation, unto the Child of Light, that yet ſits in Darkneſs, being deeply afflicted, and wounded in ſpirit, through ignorance of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the New Covenant, in Chriſt Jeſus the Light.</head>
               <p>DEar Child, of the Birth of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Seed, which cries over all the World, and beyond all the Pleaſures, Pomp and Vanity therein, for the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the light Countenance of God, fear thou not, neither be thou diſcouraged becauſe of the violent aſſaults of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who ſeeks to draw thee into the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reaſonings of thy ſpirit, and in it to kindle a fire to thy ſelf, and cauſe thee to walk in the light of the ſparks that thou haſt kindled; and this thou haſt at the hand of the Lord, in going from his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, lyeſt down in ſorrow; few knows thy great diſtreſs, but to the Lord it is known, and to them that had, and walked in the ſame paths.</p>
               <p>Oh thou beloved Babe, who lieſt in the deep ſence of the working of the evil-one in thy mind, and many times art ready to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152237:75"/>
ſay, <hi>Never was any like unto me, neither any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow!</hi> and in this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing deſpairing mournings of thy ſoul, all things made bitter unto thee as the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Marah;</hi> thus art thou driven from all comfort, as a Child without a Father, and a deſolate Widdow without a Husband, and as a Stranger that no eye pittieth, in thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; ſometimes ſaying in thy heart, in the heat of the temptation, and the fire that thou haſt kindled, O that I had been any Creature but what I am! or if it were the Will of the Lord, that he would ſhorten my dayes, that I might not be any longer on Earth to ſin againſt him! for in thy own ſence and feeling thou walking in the ſparks thou haſt kindled in carnal reaſonings, thou deſerveſt not any thing but Wrath, Horror, Miſery and Diſtreſs on every ſide, and great languiſhings that thy dayes were ſhortened, ſecretly crying out in thy heart, <hi>O that I were alone in the Wilderneſs, or any Cave or Den in the Earth, that I might never ſet nor hear any of the Sons of men any more, but in the ſecret, retiredneſs even roar and mourn out my dayes until I die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O thou Royal Child of the birth of the morning of the pure eternal Day of the God
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152237:76"/>
of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hearken no longer to the enemy, who ſaith, <hi>There hath none travelled where thou art, nor none drunk of the Cup that thou art drinking;</hi> he is a Lyar who goes about to deſtroy thy precious ſoul. In the Word of the Lord God I declare unto thee, I drank the ſame cup with my faithful Friends, who are born of the Royal Seed, every one in their meaſures travelled in the ſame path, and have endured the ſame temptations, and walked in the light of the ſame ſparks, and laid down in ſorrow in the ſence of the ſame miſery as thou mourneſt under this day; no longer lend an ear to the enemy and the thoughts of thy heart: Ariſe, ariſe in the Light of the Covenant ſtay thy heart, and the Lord will throw down the Enemy of thy peace, deſtroy the carnal reaſonings of thy mind, put out the fire that thou haſt kindled, and he will deliver thee out of the horrible Pit, and ſet thy feet upon the Rock of Ages; and thou ſhalt tread down the enemies of thy ſoul in the ſenſible feeling of the Love of the Father, who will manifeſt himſelf to be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Fatherleſs in thee, and a Husband to the mournful Widdow, and a Comforter to the Immortal Babe that mourns in thee, in the uprightneſs of thy heart to do the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:152237:76"/>
Will of the Living God; ſo in the power of his Might ſtay thy heart, and tread upon all doubts, fears, diſpairing thoughts, queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, reaſonings, muſings, imaginations and conſultings; ariſe over them all in the Light of Chriſt, he will lead thee into the Banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houſe of the Pleaſure of our God, where thou ſhalt ſit down with me, and all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed of my Father, who are born of the Immortal Seed, and have paſſed through great Tribulations, &amp; have waſhed our Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and made them white in the Blood of the Lamb, therefore do we now ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of God, praiſing him day and night in his Holy Temple. And this ſhall be the portion of thy Cup, if thou dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently hearken to the Counſel of the Lord, which calls thee to truſt in him, he will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee in the arms of his Love, and thou ſhalt praiſe his Name for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God Almighty, in his Light and Life, raiſe up thy ſoul, and eſtabliſh thy heart in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, ſtedfaſtly to wait in his Power to lead thee in the Croſs, out of all unbelief, and cauſe thee to lie down at reſt, in obedience to his Will, where thou ſhalt drink the Cup of Salvation for ever. Farewel.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Dewsbury.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
